<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The treasure of tranquillity. Or A manuall of morall discourses tending to the tranquillity of minde. Translated out of French by I.M. Master of Arts.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855031</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20501</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20501)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1086:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The treasure of tranquillity. Or A manuall of morall discourses tending to the tranquillity of minde. Translated out of French by I.M. Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Maxwell, James, b. 1581.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42], 155, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Samuel Rand, and are to be sold at his shop neere Holborne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by James Maxwell, of the French original.</note>
                  <note>Errata on a10r.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A manuall of morall discourses.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:1"/>
            <p>THE TREASVRE Of Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>OR A MANVALL OF Morall Diſcourſes, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Tranquillity of Minde.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French by <hi>T. M.</hi> Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, for SAMVEL RAND, and are to be ſold at his Shop neere Holborne Bridge 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE IOHN LORD RAMSEY, Vicount of HADINGTON, The moſt valorous Reſcuer of our King: And to the right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vertuous Lady, ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH Vicounteſſe of HADINTON, his <hi>wife, Honours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EHOLD I bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Honours, this Engliſh <hi>Treaſure of tranquility of minde.</hi> It is a treaſure, and therefore wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb facs="tcp:20501:3"/>
of you, who in the iudgement of all thoſe that full know your worth, are worthy of the beſt Treaſure that either Nature or Arte, honour or wealth are able to yeeld, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be but a ſmall one (for how ſhall a meane man giue any great gift) and euen ſo ſmall that eaſily ye may hold it in one of your hands (in which regard I confeſſe it is but too vnworthy of your greatneſſe) yet my wiſh is that it may ſerue for a teſtimony, howſoeuer ſmall, of that no ſmall affection and obſeruancie which vnto your Honours I doe beare: till at what time ſome greater token of my duty appeare, and come forth into the light vnder the luſtre of your honourable name.</p>
            <p>This little <hi>Manual</hi> doth intreat of ſuch morall meanes as may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man to the attaining of true <hi>Tranquillity;</hi> the which the <hi>Poets</hi> haue painted out for the pretiouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20501:3"/>
thereof vnder the names of <hi>Nectar</hi> and <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> the dilicious bread and drinke of their gods, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giuing vs to vnderſtand, that the vertue and efficacy thereof is ſuch that it is no leſſe able to make men like vnto God by felicity, then were <hi>Circes</hi> ſenſual cuppes to transforme men into ſwine by carnall voluptie. In it one ſhall ſee how a man may best fortifie himſelfe againſt the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent flaſhings of his affections and the vnreaſonable and vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vproares of his paſſions, and how he may attaine vnto the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſame, and to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelfe. In it may likewiſe be ſeene how and in what manner a man must carry himſelfe about cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, charges and employments, both before, and after his vndertaking of them, how to order the whole impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant actions of his life. It will ſhew a man how to foreſee by prouidence
<pb facs="tcp:20501:4"/>
and foreſight all kinde of changes, and chances that vſually do occurre, and how to comport our ſelues in them, and to keep a correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with them, by carrying our ſelues patiently in aduerſity, and moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in proſperity. Laſtly, in it a man may learne how to correct, or couer humors, how to make choice of friends, and how to make vſe both of other folkes fortunes, and his owne. All which instructions and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein mentioned, in the moſt briefe and bright manner, may ſerue very much for the attaining of this foreſaid Tranquility, The learned Biſhop <hi>Don Antonio Gueuara</hi> in his <hi>Caſtiliane</hi> diſcourſe, dedicated to the King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> touching the miſeries and vanities of the Court, thinketh it a matter almoſt impoſſible for a Courtier to attaine thereunto ſo long as he followeth the Court, in regard of the manifold
<pb facs="tcp:20501:4"/>
vexations of minde, which there doe ariſe, becauſe of couetouſneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, emulation, and ambition which commonly at Court are ſo rife: the which graue Biſhops iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if it be true, then truely Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers ſtand in much more neede of ſuch furtherances of true <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility</hi> as this is, then do other men, and yet I dare perſwade my ſelfe that your Lordſhips owne ſelfe doth ſtand in much leſſe neede of ſuch morall helpes, then many other doe. For ye are ſo farre from couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (which morall Writers do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call the cankerworme of Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers) that your bounty and liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is euery where knowne, and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly ſpoken of: and ſo free from ambition the Burriour of Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that your modeſty and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to euery one more then mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. The riſing and exaltation of men is vſually ſubiect to enuy, but it
<pb facs="tcp:20501:5"/>
is your Lordſhip good fortune that no man enuieth your good fortune, yea rather men wonder how that it is not much more fauourable then it is, conſidering the greatneſſe of your extraordinary deſert, and your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matched moderation in this your Lordſhips preſent preferment. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluing and reading the Chronicles of our Countrie written by our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Hector Boece,</hi> and by our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Leſly,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Roſſe,</hi> the ornament of our Ile, I find that the ancient name of <hi>Ramſey</hi> hath in former times afoorded diuers fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and King-fauoured perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, your Lordſhips Anceſtors and honourable kinſmen, which haue done acceptable ſeruice to their Countrie and Kings. Such a one was ſir <hi>Alexander Ramſey</hi> of <hi>Dale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> Knight, who in King <hi>Dauid Bruces</hi> time, was a moſt vertuous wight, and according to the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:20501:5"/>
of his name in Greeke) proued another <hi>Greeke-alexander</hi> euen a moſt ſtrong helper of men. For hee is recorded to haue bene the moſt worthy Chiefetaine of thoſe dayes, and ſo renowmed for his proweſſe that euery Noble man was faine to haue his ſonne or kinſ-man to ſerue vnder him. Such a one likewiſe was Sir <hi>William Ramſey,</hi> preferred in the ſaid Kings time, to be Earle of <hi>Fife,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Ramſey</hi> maiſter houſhold to King <hi>Iames</hi> the third, and his greateſt minion and fauourite preferred to be Earle <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwell,</hi> Theſe and ſuch others, no doubt but that they deſerued well, each of them in his place: but all <hi>Albion,</hi> yea all <hi>Europe</hi> knoweth that your deſert is of a farre more notable kind. God who giueth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance vnto Kings and reſcueth <hi>Dauid</hi> his ſeruant from the hurtful ſword, did vſe you as an inſtrument
<pb facs="tcp:20501:6"/>
for the reſcuing of our Soueraigne vpon <hi>Mars</hi> his day, and in that towne and place, where once <hi>Cune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagius</hi> King of <hi>Britaines</hi> builded a Temple vnto <hi>Mars.</hi> The two too martially, and mortally affected men on their <hi>Mars-day,</hi> and in their <hi>Mars-towne,</hi> would haue to their bloody Idol <hi>Mars</hi> ſacrificed the heart-bloud of their King: But God in heauen who is the true <hi>Mars,</hi> euen the God of Hoſtes, and the moſt mighty reſcuer of Kings on earth, kept his ſeruants heart in his hand, &amp; by your happy hand preuented the spilling of his bloud, yea more, hee made themſelues the bloudy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and you the ſacrificer. On the fift of August, they thought to haue made our <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to taſt of death, and to guſte of the graue. But God turned the day of our <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> danger into a day of deliuerance for him, and of deſtruction for his
<pb facs="tcp:20501:6"/>
enemies, and as the Lord made it a day of preſeruation vnto our King, ſo hath he made it a day of gratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and thankeſ-giuing vnto the Lord, for that his vnſpeakeable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. The ſame is likewiſe the Calender day of commemoration of the moſt godly and deuout King <hi>Saint Oſwald,</hi> who was a King ful of piety towards God, and of pitty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore, as <hi>Galfride Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſbury, Polychronicon,</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Beda</hi> do write. And who King <hi>Iames-like</hi> was an vniting King, euen of the two diuided King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Northumberland, Deira,</hi> &amp; <hi>Bernicia,</hi> and a teaching, yea a Preaching, and a conuerting King. For after his returning home out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whether he had fled for feare of his too ſtrong foes, where he had enioyed protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with Princely liberty, the space of <hi>18.</hi> yeares, and where hee together with his brother
<pb facs="tcp:20501:7"/>
               <hi>Oſwy</hi> with many other yong Nobles had bene chriſtned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the faith by the holy <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Biſhop <hi>Aidanus,</hi> as <hi>Beda</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, he wholly gaue himſelfe to the conuerſion of his heatheniſh ſubiects to the Chriſtian faith, and for the ſame purpoſe he ſent into <hi>Scotland</hi> for <hi>Aidanus,</hi> whom he made Biſhop of <hi>Lindefarne,</hi> and Primate of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> vnto whom alſo ſucceded diuers other holy men of the ſame Country, namely <hi>Finanus, Colmanus, Cuthbertus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Euen this godly King was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to expound the Sermons and inſtructions which <hi>Aidanus</hi> made in the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> language, to his people in the <hi>Engliſh Saxon</hi> tongue: ſo that with greater reaſon may he be called, the <hi>Prince of Preachers,</hi> then was <hi>Henry</hi> the fift called the <hi>Prince of Prieſts</hi> as Chronicles doe beare. For <hi>Oſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:7"/>
was not aſhamed in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to teach and expound to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Principels of the Chriſtian faith, and that in publicke, whereas the moſt vertuous, valorous, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorius Prince <hi>Henry</hi> the fift (the father of that moſt pious and patient Prince <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt) yea and the flowre of the whole <hi>Henries,</hi> and most worthy to be a patterne for our yong hopefull <hi>Henry</hi> to imitate, was called the <hi>Prince of Prieſts,</hi> for no other cauſe, but for that he did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect his Prieſts &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates exceedingly, and tooke a great care for their honourable prouiſion like another <hi>Ezekiah.</hi> This bleſſed King <hi>Oſwald,</hi> though in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he got a great victory ouer his too strong enemies, being many more in number then he, at his erected croſſe in <hi>Heauen-field;</hi> yet in the end he fell <hi>Ioſiah-like</hi> by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh hand of wicked <hi>Penda</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:20501:8"/>
               <hi>Mercian</hi> King, and that on the fift day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> being but a litle elder then our Soueraigne was on that ſame day of his danger, Good Lord! how great a lamentation was there made in the North, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as holy King <hi>Oſwald</hi> fel in the field of <hi>Maxfield</hi> by the hand of the heatheniſh <hi>Penda</hi> the <hi>Mercian</hi> King? euen ſuch a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation as was made in the South when good King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> fell in the field of <hi>Megiddo,</hi> by the heatheniſh hand of the Egyptian King <hi>Pharao Necho?</hi> And what great mourning ſhould there haue beene made both North and South, if our <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and our <hi>Oſwald,</hi> being almoſt of the ſame age with them, who were equall in yeares all ſaue one, had fallen on that day with them by the hands of thoſe two conſpiring <hi>Pendas,</hi> and by the reuenging hands of two hard-hearted <hi>Pharaohs?</hi> For as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is as much as reuenging in the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:8"/>
ſo were they two ſet vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge for their father, as the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother did confeſſe. But it was the Lords will that they ſhould proue <hi>Pharao Nechos,</hi> and yet that in the meane time our <hi>Ioſiah</hi> ſhould be ſafe. That is to ſay, that our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne ſhould <hi>Iacob-like</hi> proue a ſupplanter of his enemies, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be a <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that is a burning light of the Lords to this land: &amp; that thoſe children of reuenge, ſhould proue lame reuengers, and ſuch as were ſmitten, for ſo doe theſe words of <hi>Pharao Necho</hi> ſignifie. They plotted miſchiefe in their hearts, and they would haue practiſed miſchiefe with their hands: and therefore the Lord made them lame in their hearts, and in their hands, euen both heartleſſe and handleſſe: ſo that they had neither policy, nor power to execute their intended, and pretended reuenge, yea more they were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:20501:9"/>
both by your hand, who did hit them on the teeth, and thunder on them ſo ſore that thoſe euill men were blotted out from among men, and caſt away like two forlorne caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes, in ſo doing your worthy actions did anſwere vnto the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of your ſurname: for as <hi>Ram</hi> ſignifieth as much in Hebrew as high and caſting away, ſo doth <hi>Rameſes</hi> ſignifie a thunder, a hitting in the teeth, and a blotting out euill.</p>
            <p>At what time the ſunne was in running of his Giants race, being mounted on the backe of the <hi>celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Lion,</hi> euen from <hi>Aries</hi> top to <hi>Piſces</hi> taile; and that <hi>Albions Sun</hi> was running his race vnder <hi>Aries,</hi> (which according to <hi>Ptolomee,</hi> and the Aſtrologians, is the celestiall ſigne of this head-Ile of men, as it is of the head of man,) being moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the backe of a <hi>Lilly-bearing Lion,</hi> running as it were, with the
<pb facs="tcp:20501:9"/>
               <hi>Leopard,</hi> from <hi>Kentire</hi> to <hi>Kent,</hi> and from <hi>Catneſſe</hi> to <hi>Totneſſe,</hi> for the priſe of the Roſen Crowne: At that ſame time, and euen when as he was come almoſt to his rinks end, and ready to lay hold vpon the prize, the <hi>Deuouring Lyon</hi> began to roare and rampe, and neuer to take any reſt from compaſſing till he had ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp ſome compaſſing <hi>Sheba</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> the beloued of the Lord, as the word ſignifieth: For <hi>Iacob</hi> hath hee loued. But behold the <hi>Lion of Iudah,</hi> who feedeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Lillies,</hi> and taketh pleaſure in the gathering of <hi>Lillies,</hi> (as the ſpouſe in the Canticles ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) euen he holpe his <hi>Lilly-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lion,</hi> and put into your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips yong heart the courage of a <hi>luſty Lion</hi> for the confounding of the old <hi>Deuouring Lions</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, our <hi>Lilly-Lions</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. Thus the <hi>Old Lion</hi> miſſed of his proiect,
<pb facs="tcp:20501:10"/>
and the <hi>Lilly-bearing-Lion</hi> ere it was long wan the prize.</p>
            <p>In the ſpring time, and in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof, when all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſpring and to ſprout, the <hi>Lilly</hi> of the <hi>North</hi> began to ſpring, and to put forth both a white and a red floure. When <hi>Phoebus,</hi> the bright eye of the world, had begun in the ſigne of <hi>Aries</hi> to ouerſhine the whole Hemiſphere, then our <hi>Phoebus,</hi> the bright ſtarre of the <hi>North,</hi> began to ouerſhine <hi>Albions</hi> whole Iſle, which is vnder <hi>Aries:</hi> yea and is as the heauen-fauoured head of Ilands, yea of lands, vnder the head of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> as is likewiſe the head of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And my wiſh is, that the whole body of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> may once full into his hands who hath already the head. <hi>Ptolomie</hi> in his Aſtrological Conſtruction, &amp; <hi>Pontanus</hi> in his coelestiall things, will ſoone ſhew a man what I meane. Our <hi>King</hi> hee euen entred to this
<pb facs="tcp:20501:10"/>
Crowne about that time that <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God</hi> entred into the world by the creation thereof, and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour entred into the world for the renouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame by the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our fleſh: euen then (I ſay) when as <hi>IESVS</hi> the ſonne of <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY,</hi> beganne in his bleſſed mothers wombe to make all thinges new, <hi>IAMES</hi> the ſonne of <hi>MARY</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his new Kingdome. At what time the Lord <hi>IESVS</hi> came downe from God in Heauen into earth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men to make an Vnion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Heauen and Earth, God and Man, yea and betweene Man and Man (for all God and Chriſts acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aime at vnion:) at that ſame time came <hi>King IAMES</hi> downe from the <hi>North</hi> into the <hi>South,</hi> to make an Vnion betweene <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> and betweene Men &amp; Men, I meane betweene his <hi>Northerne</hi> and <hi>Southerne</hi> ſubiects.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:11"/>Who as hee is ſprung from the bleſſed Bed of the white-red-roſie vnion of two royall Houſes; ſo hath the eternall Vnion-maker appointed him to be the auſpicious Author of a farre greater Lilly-roſie, and white-red-croſſie vnion of two anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Kingdomes. To the end that two (once warring and iarring) nations, might bee reconciled and vnited in allegeance and loue, as they are in religion and language. The which thing <hi>Merlin</hi> many hundred yeares agoe hath cleerely foretold in theſe tearmes: <hi>Pacificabuntur natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Regni, &amp; Leo ad ſtateram ſedebit: Bruti nomine vocabitur regnum, &amp; nuncupatio extrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum peribit.</hi> The nations and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Kingdome ſhall bee paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and vnited by the Lyon that ſhal rule. The Kingdome ſhall bee called by the name of <hi>Brutus Britany,</hi> and the other name which forrainers,
<pb facs="tcp:20501:11"/>
that is, the <hi>Saxons,</hi> or <hi>Angles,</hi> brought in, ſhall faile. Yea, the ſame <hi>Merlin</hi> hath likewiſe foretold long ago the plantation, and conformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by his Maieſties meanes in this manner: <hi>Sextus Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berniae moenia ſubuertet, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora in planitiem mutabit, di uerſas portiones in vnum redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, &amp; capite Leonis coronabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> The ſixt (ſaith hee) ſhall ding downe the walles of <hi>Ireland,</hi> that is to ſay, the thicke woods, forreſts, and trees thereof, by turning them into arable ground. The diuers portions of it ſhall bee brought into one, and it ſhall be crowned with the Lyons head.</p>
            <p>The which prediction; mee thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, ought rather to be vnderſtood of our King, who is not onely deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the ancient <hi>Iriſh Kings,</hi> no leſſe then from the <hi>Engliſh, Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh,</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh;</hi> but alſo is the
<pb facs="tcp:20501:12"/>
ſixt of the name of <hi>Iames,</hi> bearing a red Lion in his Armes, &amp; hath alſo taken order for that foretold plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Ireland:</hi> rather I ſay, then to vnderſtand it, &amp; expound, it with <hi>Alanus Magnus,</hi> of <hi>King Henry</hi> the firſt. Except hee had meant it of our hopefull floure of Princes, <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria,</hi> and of <hi>Cumbria, Albions</hi> yong Lilly-roſie-Lyon, and the firſt of that name ſince the <hi>Concord,</hi> as the other was the firſt of the ſame name from the <hi>Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally it was but a few daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the feſtiuall time of the bleſſed and glorious Saintes (according to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Calender) <hi>Iames</hi> the brother of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Mary,</hi> that Sathan <hi>Herod-like</hi> thought and ſought to haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iames,</hi> the happy ſon of a match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Mary,</hi> and the memorable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of great <hi>Britaines</hi> greatest
<pb facs="tcp:20501:12"/>
grace and vnited glory; and <hi>Anna</hi> likewiſe, a gracefull Mother of reſt, according to her name, and the happy mother of ſo many hopefull children. That great enemy of kings, yea of all mankinde, I ſay, thought euen at that time to haue ſlaine both of them, <hi>Iames</hi> with the edge of the ſword, and <hi>Anna</hi> with endleſſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. For he was ſorrie to foreſee how that a golden-roſie crowne ſhould bee ſet vpon their happy heads at this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly time. But the Lord hath preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both (and long may he preſerue, both.) and at that festiuall time, at which ſathan thought to haue fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted vpon their fall, he made their crowne to flouriſh; for hee ſet a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie crowne of pure gold vpon their heads, and clothed them with glory in the eyes of all <hi>Albion,</hi> yea, of all <hi>Europe.</hi> And hee that hath ſet the Crowne vpon their heads, will keepe it on in diſpite of the diuell, and of
<pb facs="tcp:20501:13"/>
all ſuch blind-zealed paſſionatiſts, (I will call them no worſe) as haue either ſought, or ſhall ſeeke hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to hurle downe head and crowne into the duſt, or to blow all vp into the aire.</p>
            <p>And not onely hath the great King-crowner ſet vpon his ſeruants head a crowne: yea a <hi>triple crowne of Vnion;</hi> but alſo he hath put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands an <hi>Harpe,</hi> the which as <hi>Orus Apollo</hi> writeth, is the hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicke, or ſymbole of <hi>Concorde,</hi> (for our God is a God of Concorde, and our King is a King of Concord) to the end that <hi>Dauid-like</hi> by the muſicall melodie thereof, euen by the gentle moderation of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and peaceable minde, and by the pithy and pleaſant perſwaſion of his eloquent mouth, he may chaſe away <hi>Sauls</hi> euill ſpirit of malice and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring from our mindes, and make all our partialities and priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb facs="tcp:20501:13"/>
to depart, to the end; that <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Iſraël</hi> may bee made one perfect people in vnion and affection, as well as in ſubiection; and in loue as well as in religion. And truly if we bee not worſe-ſpirited then <hi>Saul</hi> was, and more vngratefully affected then hee, <hi>Dauids</hi> harping muſt at laſt chaſe away the vncleane ſpirit of Diuiſion from our heads, and bring home the cleane and quiet ſpirit of Vnion into our hearts, that in the end both <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South</hi> may ioyne hands, and ſing to the praiſe of the God of <hi>Vnion,</hi> that ſweete har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monius ſong of <hi>Vnion: Ecce quàm bonum, &amp; quàm iucundum fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres habitare in vnum.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>O how happy a thing it is,</l>
               <l>And ioyfull for to ſee,</l>
               <l>Brethren together faſt to hold</l>
               <l>The band of Vnitie.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:14"/>And truely <hi>Dauid</hi> deſerueth a farre better requitall at our hands for his harmonious harping, then that any of his paſſionate patients, whether <hi>North</hi> or <hi>South,</hi> (for it is not the <hi>South</hi> alone that is auerſe from Vnion) ſhould with graceleſſe and grateleſſe <hi>Saul,</hi> ſeeke thus to wound his heart with the ſharpe ſpeare of obſtinate oppoſition. And yet for all this hee leaueth not off <hi>Orpheus-like,</hi> with the harmony and melody of his harpe to charme and tame the wild beaſts of our iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring affections, paſſionate oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and timorous apprehenſions, to the end that the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi> may be for euer made faithfull friends, and may euen brother-like liue and lye together (to ſpeake with the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi>) yea and dwell together as it were in one denne.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Orpheus</hi> is labouring by all meanes with the harmonie of his
<pb facs="tcp:20501:14"/>
               <hi>Harp,</hi> to turn our ſwords into ſithes, and our ſpeares into ſpades, to the end that there be no more hurting or fighting hereafter in <hi>Albion</hi> among our ſelues, and that all former troubles and by-paſt quarrels may be forgotten, according as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaketh. But if wee will needs be more vncharmable, and vntame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then were <hi>Orpheus beaſts</hi> at the ſound of his <hi>Harpe,</hi> then we ſhall haue good cauſe to feare, leaſt wee both proue at home, and bee called abroad brute-anes indeed. For if we will bite and backe-bite one another like dogges in the beginning; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leaſt like the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Leopard,</hi> we conſume one another in the end. The which euill thing, I pray the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Vnion,</hi> who is likewiſe the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> euen of our <hi>Iacob,</hi> and of his <hi>Albion,</hi> yea and of his <hi>Albions Vnion</hi> for euer to forbid.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:15"/>The Lord who is the Author of <hi>Vnion,</hi> and whoſe nature is <hi>Vnion,</hi> as his number is Vnitie, had purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make his ſeruant the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Vnion.</hi> Euen <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Prince of of peace, who is our peace, and hath made of both, one, by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king downe the ſtop of the partition wall, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) hee had appointed to make <hi>Iames</hi> his ſeruant to be <hi>Britaines</hi> peace, and to make of both kingdomes one, by breaking downe the partition-wall of partialities, oppoſitions, paſſionate affections, and priuate reſpects. That great <hi>King-crowner,</hi> and matchleſſe <hi>Vnion-maker,</hi> I ſay, had euen determined to adorne and decore his ſeruants head with an <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion-diademne,</hi> whoſe price (like vnto King <hi>Lemuels</hi> vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) is farre aboue the pearles. And hence it is, that his enemies, which imagined miſchiefe, &amp; inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:20501:15"/>
euill against his ſacred perſon; in the <hi>North</hi> to hurle him downe into an hole, in the <hi>South</hi> to blowe him vp vnto the Pole, could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee our ſoueraigne gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly preſerued, and in a manner gloriouſly transfigured in the ſight of his louing ſubiects, at the ſame time that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> was moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and viſibly transfigured vppon mount <hi>Tabor</hi> in the ſight of his three principall Apostles, <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> I ſay hee was in a manner transfigured at that ſame time, becauſe at that ſame time, of a ſuppoſed dead man he was found to bee aliue, and in effect did paſſe, or was tranſlated from death to life. Yea more, of a Prince hee was transformed into a Preacher, and a publiſher of Gods powerfull preſeruation, ſhewed in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and of his praiſes for the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:20501:16"/>
in the middes of the Congregation of the people. The which hee did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in the moſt publicke manner, and in the moſt publicke place, euen vpon the croſſie Mountaine of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and contrition (for ſo doth the word <hi>Tabor</hi> ſignifie,) I meane in the middes of the choyſeſt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Cittie of the <hi>North, Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> At which time hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared more pretious, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the eyes of all his loyall and louing ſubiects, then euer hee had done before. Yea euen ſo precious, and ſo deere, that the eyes of the multitude could not bee ſatisfied e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with beholding him, both when as hee was vpon the Croſſie-mountaine, and when as he was come downe.</p>
            <p>True it is, that there were ſome which could not at firſt with incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous <hi>Thomas</hi> be perſwaded of the <hi>Truth,</hi> except that they had either
<pb facs="tcp:20501:16"/>
ſeene or felt the very wounds and blowes vpon our Soueraignes Body, neither could bee brought to giue trust to the true testimony of a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea a touching <hi>Thomas,</hi> euen of a Noble <hi>Earskin</hi> an honourable branch of honour (according to the <hi>Saxon</hi> ſignification of his ſurname) I meane my Lord <hi>Vicount Fenton,</hi> then a valourous <hi>Reſcuer</hi> of our King, and now the worthy Captaine of his Guard, and both then and now, one of his Highneſſe beſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeruants. Neither could the teſtimony of your Lordſhips owne ſelfe, à ſeeing, yea à touching <hi>Iohn,</hi> preuaile with them, though your te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony was euen ſealed, not onely with the conſpirators bloud, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with your owne, whereof ye had the markes then to ſhew, and as yet ſtill keepe the skarre thereof in your skin. But both, theſe haue bene better informed ſince, and the better part
<pb facs="tcp:20501:17"/>
then, was fully perſwaded of the Truth, &amp; eſteemed that they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as it were, a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this notable preſeruation and real transfiguration of their Prince. <hi>This is my ſeruant in whom I am well pleaſed, obey him, honour him, and thanke God for him:</hi> yea all his good ſubiects and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants there preſent ſaid in effect with <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn, It is good for vs to bee heere,</hi> It is good for vs to be here to ſee our King in ſafety, it is good for vs to haue ſuch a Lord as the Lord loueth, ſuch a maiſter as is Gods ſeruant, &amp; ſuch a King, as the immortall King kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth. <hi>And the King himſelfe:</hi> it is good for me to haue ſuch ſubiects and ſeruants, as loue me ſo dearely that they cannot bee filled with loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on me, after my danger, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery, and it is good for me to haue ſuch a foreward and toward ſeruant
<pb facs="tcp:20501:17"/>
in my neede and at a pinch as my yong <hi>Ramſey.</hi> And truely my Lord euen as your Chriſten name ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Grace,</hi> and the place where firſt your vertue did appeare, ſignifieth the towne of <hi>Grace,</hi> and as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whoſe cauſe it did appeare is a Prince full of <hi>Grace;</hi> ſo me thinketh that God hath wonderfully graced you in that he would haue your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to appeare in this kind, and at that time: and in that he would haue the beginning of your Lordſhips ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation to fall out in the time of his ſons glorious transfiguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for euen then did the Lord begin to call you vp from the low valley of worſhip, into the high hill of honour, where ye were transfigured from the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Kings Page,</hi> vnto the <hi>Kings preſeruer.</hi> Whereupon, of a Gentleman by birth and bloud, yee were within a while made a <hi>Noble Baron,</hi> yea and a worthy <hi>Vicount:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:18"/>
and that which I had almost forgot (pardon me I pray you, for it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your L<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. order hath not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or patronal name) of a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Squire</hi> ye were dubbed a coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Knight. And though you be not of any patronized order, as of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtinian, White-croſſie</hi> order of <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> according both to your Lordſhips name, and the name of the place (being called <hi>S. Iohns towne</hi>) where your vertue and knightly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour did fiſt ſhew it ſelfe, nor yet of the <hi>Caſtilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Red-croſſie</hi> order of <hi>S. Iames,</hi> according to the name of the feſtiuall time, neere vnto which your Lordſhips vertue did appeare, as alſo of the perſon, in whoſe cauſe yee did ſo generouſly, and valourouſly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture your ſelfe, nor yet of any of the two <hi>Aragonian</hi> orders, the one <hi>Black-croſſie</hi> the other <hi>Red-croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Iames</hi> King of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> though I ſay your Lordſhips
<pb facs="tcp:20501:18"/>
Knighthood hath not any ſuch note or name, yet I am aſſured that all worthy perſonages will honour your Knightly courage, and deferre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your vertue and worth, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you for <hi>King Iames his reſcuing Knight:</hi> and this will ſerue you in steed of a <hi>Saint Iames</hi> or a King <hi>Iames</hi> his order of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bion.</hi> But to ſhut vp, at laſt, my diſcourſing dedication, for the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe whereof I muſt implore your Lordſhips, and the courteous Readers fauourable excuſe: as I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your Lordſhip for your worth, and your well deſeruing of our King, and whole Countrie, both <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South;</hi> ſo muſt I tell you, that you are infinitely beholden vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God for your good fortune: whether ye regard your Lordſhips honorable exaltation, or yet your happy aſſociation in mariage with a gracefull <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the eldest
<pb facs="tcp:20501:19"/>
daughter of the Noble <hi>Earle</hi> and <hi>Counteſſe</hi> of <hi>Suſſex.</hi> The which your Lordſhips alliance with ſo anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and honourable an houſe, I doubt not but ye doe eſteeme as one of the chiefest degrees of your Lordſhips earthly felicity. Your Lordſhip know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who hath ſaid it, <hi>honorantes me, honorabo,</hi> ſuch as honour me, I will honour. Goe on therefore in proouing thankefull vnto God for the honour which hee hath already giuen you, and yet hee will giue you more. For according to the meaſure of your honouring of God, ſhall God make you to be honoured of man; it is an eaſie thing for the great King of hearts to open yet a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der doore in our <hi>Salomons</hi> large heart to let you in, and when he hath once opened the doore, it is as eaſie a thing for him to ſhut it ſo faſt, that ye ſhall neuer go out of it, for he that hath the key of <hi>Dauid</hi> which ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:20501:19"/>
and no man ſhutteth, &amp; ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and no man openeth: hath alſo the key of our <hi>Dauids</hi> heart in his hand, and hee openeth, or ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame, when and to whom it pleaſeth him. Your L<hi rend="sup">s</hi> ſurname was one of thoſe that did fauor the right of <hi>Edgar Etheling</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> crown at the Conqueſt: and therefore was forced to ſlie with <hi>Edgar</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> as our renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Leſlie Biſhop of Roſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hector Boece</hi> with others, do write. And in <hi>Scotland</hi> it was endowed with lands, liuings, &amp; Lordſhips, &amp; decored with Titles of honour in the perſons of diuers of your L<hi rend="sup">s</hi> honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble anceſtors &amp; kinſmen, as I ſhew in ſome particulars mentioned aboue, though not in all. And now againe it is come into <hi>England,</hi> whence once it did ſpring, to reuiue, now after the <hi>Concord,</hi> the ancient honor which it had before the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> in your Lordſhips noble perſon.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:20"/>that euen as God hath made you the inſtrument of much honour and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite vnto both countries by the meanes of your vertue, and reſcuing hand, ſo may yee beare or reape the fruite of honour in both Countries. But least I ſeeme to ſome to ſpeake too much, heere I ſtay, wiſhing vnto your Lordſhip, and your worthy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for your ſtay, the fulneſſe of Gods grace (according to the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your two chriſten vnited names) together with the highest ſtep and top of ſtable honour; and ſo I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours right de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted to all humble duties. IAMES MAXVVELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:20"/>
            <head>The Contents of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISCOVRSE I.</hi> HOw we muſt prepare our ſelues againſt the aſſaults and onſets of our paſsions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISCOVR. 2.</hi> Of the choice of callings, charges and affaires,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 3.</hi> Of prouidence and foreſight.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 4.</hi> Of each mans vocation and calling.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 5.</hi> Of a mans ruling and ordering his life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 6.</hi> Of the diuerſity of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20501:21"/>
                  <hi>DISC. 7.</hi> Of the choice of friends.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 8.</hi> Of diſſembling and diſguiſing of humors.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 9.</hi> Of Vanitie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 10.</hi> Of proſperity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 11.</hi> Of comparing of our fortune with that of others.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 12.</hi> Of aduerſity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 13.</hi> Of ſadneſse and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 14.</hi> Of the afflictions of good men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 15.</hi> Of other mens faults and imperfections.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 16.</hi> Of iniuries, indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and wrongs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 17.</hi> Of pouerty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>DISC. 18.</hi> Of death our laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and our laſt debt.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:21"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. for tried, read had. pag. 26. for euer read euen. 34. for euer, read neuer. pag. 86. for continuance, read continence. pag. 92. for ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, read can. pag. 104. for wretchleſly, read retchleſly. pag. 130. for mighty viſions, read nightly viſions. pag. 140. for miſteeme, read miſken. pag. 150. for to iue, read to liue. pag. 153. for the fore, read to the fore. pag. Ibid. for riotous, read with riotous.</p>
            <p>Such faults as are in the pointing, the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Reader will eaſily eſpy, and as I hope, courteouſly excuſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20501:22"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20501:22"/>
            <head>A Manuall of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Diſcourſes, tending to Tranquility of <hi>Minde,</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="discourse">
               <head>DISCOVRSE. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How we muſt prepare our ſelues againſt the aſſaults and onſets of our paſſions.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONſidering that our happines on earth doth hang (next after the knowledge of Chriſt) vpon our actions, and that the ſoule is, as it were, the Fountaine and wel-ſpring thereof; our chiefe care (if we deſire to liue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20501:23"/>
an happy life) ſhould be to make the better part of vs quiet and calm, endeauoring by al meanes, that it be not troubled, nor diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by vulgar &amp; popular opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as being things much contrary to the excellent nature thereof.</p>
               <p>There are two times, the one of proſperity, the other of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, wherein the ſoule is wont to bee vexed and toſſed, with the paſſions of the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our part, as with ſo many vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and impetuous winds. And therefore we muſt herein imitate the Mariners, which before they looſe off from the port, doe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh themſelues with all things neceſſary and needfull for reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the tempeſt and ſtorme: ſo muſt wee prouide our ſelues aforehand of ſuch ſound and ſubſtantiall diſcourſe, as may anker &amp; ſtay the minde againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20501:23"/>
the puſh of our paſſions, when as they, like ſo many ſurging waues, do, nil we, will wee, fling themſelues aboard into our boate, and euen as <hi>Xenophon</hi> did exhort his fellow Cittizens to ſacrifice vnto God in the time of proſperity, to the end they might finde him the more ready and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable when as they ſhould inuoke him in their aduerſity: So ſhould we doe, and withall, at our firſt leaſure, wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract acquaintance with rectified reaſon, to the end, that when wee ſhall ſtand in need of her aide and aſiſtance, ſhe may come running to vs at our call, as knowing vs by our voyce, and hauing already an affectionate &amp; earneſt deſire for our defence.</p>
               <p>The diſcourſe of rectified rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is the maiſter and daunter of all peeuiſh and peruerſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20501:24"/>
or paſſions. For, when as we haue once taken good notice of them by an earneſt examination and tryall, made and tryed tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame; and that wee haue ripely and aduiſedly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both what power they haue ouer vs, and what Empire wee hold ouer them: They are not thereafter ſo fierce, and furious in our behalfe, but are more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, and with much leſſe adoe appeaſed and pacified. They therein not a little reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our little dogges, which will barke vnceſſantly at ſuch as they are wont to ſee, but by and by are quieted as ſoone as they heare the voyce of ſuch as they know.</p>
               <p>The wiſe haue compared the commandement of the minde aboue this ſenſuall and terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of the ſoule, out of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20501:24"/>
which our paſſions doe ſpring, vnto the office of a Rider, who teaching, and training his horſe, and ſitting within the ſaddle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageth and turneth him at his will. But ſmall credit ſhould the Rider receiue, that ſhould bring to the Tourneyment or Tilte a yong horſe, which had neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore borne the bit, nor galloped in the round, But hee muſt needs in the firſt place breake him by conuenient diſcipline, before he vſe him in any errand or action of importance. In like manner before we put our backes vnder the burthen of any buſineſſe, or expoſe our ſelues vnto the publicke view of the world, we muſt endeauour to breake and bring vnder this wild &amp; vnbac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked part of the ſoule, and make it, as it were, to bite vpon the bit, by bringing it to learne the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20501:25"/>
lawes and meaſures whereby it muſt be managed, and maiſtered in all occaſions, and at all occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, &amp; in the meane time we muſt not forget to enhearten and encourage it, by acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it with the pleaſure and contentement, wherewith is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied the iſſue and end of all worthy and vertuous actions.</p>
               <p>Meditation and Diſcourſe is that which giueth an edge vnto the ſoule, and maketh it ſteele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard and vnpierceable, euen vnto the ſharpeſt point of the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt paſſion, &amp; vſually we proue admirable at euery ſuch exerciſe as we haue before hand accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our ſelues vnto, what diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty ſoeuer it may ſeem to carry with it. On the other ſide, there is nothing (bee it neuer ſo eaſie) which will not ſeeme hard and difficult, and withall much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20501:25"/>
vs, if it do finde vs but noui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and new apprentiſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. How often thinke yee, muſt <hi>Canius</hi> haue needs thought vpon death, and reuolued in his mind what thing it ſhould bee, who being condemned by the Tirant, and ſent to the place of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was ſo farre from being any whit diſmayed thereat in his minde, that merrily, and as it were ieſtingly, he bid the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, who came for him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he was ſtronger by the aduantage of one table, then he againſt whom hee played at that houre? And who taking his leaue of his neereſt and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt acquaintance, for his laſt farewell, vttered no other words but theſe: <hi>Now my deere friends, I ſhall preſently finde that which I haue ſo long longed after, &amp; ſo much deſired to know, if the ſoule bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20501:26"/>
and whether men in dying, do feele the ſeparation of the Soule and Body which they indure?</hi> We muſt needes thinke that this poore Pagane had a long time exerciſed himſelfe in comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ouer-ruling his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that hee had aforehand armed and fenced himſelfe with faire reſolutions, ſeeing that with ſuch conſtancy, and grauity he went to vndergo a death both cruell and vniuſt. If the onely deſire to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what ſhould become of the ſoule after death, could make the torment, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not onely tollerable, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo acceptable vnto him, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution then ought the certaine and aſſured knowledge of the ſoules immortality, together with the hope of eternall felicity worke in ſuch as doe ſeriouſly meditate vpon the ſame in their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20501:26"/>
mindes? May not theſe goods, thinke ye, make vnto ſuch minds not onely ſupportable, but euen comfortable &amp; delectable, both death it ſelfe, and all other diſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous afflictions, which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, ſeeing they are as the waues which do puſh vs forward vnto the ſweete and ſure port of euerlaſting reſt and repoſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discourse">
               <head>DIS. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the choyce of Callings and Affaires.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MAn is not borne to liue his armes a croſſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as one of the faireſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this faire frame, he muſt confer, and contribute his whole trauell and paine to the condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and conſeruation of that ciuill ſocietie and condition wherein hee is placed. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20501:27"/>
that of the choyce which men make of a calling, their reſt and quietneſſe doth principally depend, and that nothing doth ſo much auaile to the leading of a contented life, as when they find themſelues fit for the ſame: they ought, me thinketh, before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, to take a tryall of their owne ſtrength, and ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bethinke themſelues of that charge which they are about to embrace. Becauſe vſually wee preſume too much vpon our owne power, and attempt more then our ability is fit to atchieue. And this error we ſee is incident almoſt to all our actions: hence it is, that ſome will diſpend more then their meanes may well beare: Others in labouring and toyling goe beyond their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; ſome are not maiſters of their owne anger; others there</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discourse">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20501:27"/>
               <head>DISC. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of prouidence and foreſight.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>YEe muſt take order that yee be not ſurpriſed of any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine accident, whereof (if it be poſſible) yee haue not bene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand prudently foreſeene, which thing yee ſhall eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, if in all the affaires yee ſhall take in hand, in the firſt place ye doe diligently fore-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke your ſelfe of ſuch incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences and croſſe encounters as may fall out in the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature, quality, and ordinary iſſue of the affaires: and certainely ſuch foreſight doth maruailouſly mittigate, ſweeten, and abate the ſharpnes, and harſhnes of all ſuch ſiniſter accidents and chances: the which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not bring you in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20501:28"/>
any ſenſible, or notable alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and change, by reaſon of their not comming vpon you as vnlooked for, But contrarily they doe not a little endamage ſuch perſons as ſuffer themſelues to be ſurpriſed, neither do conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how that nature ſending the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into this world, hath allotted them rough, and vneaſy ſeates. Such men doe not minde how that about their owne dores many times they haue with their eyes ſeene the louing wiues weeping and bewailing their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed husbands, and the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands with dewy eyes burying their beloued wiues, and deere children. They doe not pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how that ſuch perſons as did yeſterday walke, and talke with them, to day dead, lye buried in their graues. So apt are we to be deceiued, and ſo little fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20501:28"/>
haue we in our owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that what we ſee daily with our eyes happen vnto others, we neuer, or ſildome conſider that the like may befall our owne ſelues.</p>
               <p>If we would take ſuch notice of things as wee ought, wee ſhould rather find occaſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs to maruaile how that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſters, and dangers, which doe follow vs at the heeles, haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed ſo long to ouertake vs, and hauing ouertaken vs, how it could bee poſſible that they ſhould haue handled vs ſo harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and gently as they haue done. O how groſly we deceiue our ſelues, when as for feare that men take vs to be timerous and feareful, we thinke ill to forecaſt and foreſee dangers, and will not a whit miſtruſt our owne iudgement! It behooueth the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20501:29"/>
man who is minded to make ſaile, to know that hee is in the poſſibility to haue a ſtorme, and wee muſt know that the chance which hath hapned to one may likewiſe befall vnto vs, and that which hangeth ouer the heads of all, may fall vpon any one of vs all, without exemption or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception whatſoeuer. The man who marketh well anothers miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune as a thing which may no leſſe befall vnto himſelfe, then it hath already done vnto his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, hath this aduantage, that before any ſuch miſchance take hold of him, he is already armed againſt the fury and force of the euill. Then were it too late for a man to make head againſt a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, when it is already come, &amp; bootleſſe ſhould it be for him to ſay, I did not think, forſooth, that ſuch a miſ-fortune ſhould haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20501:29"/>
befalne mee. And why ſo I pray you? is there any wealth in this world which hath not following after at her heeles pouerty and need? or is there any health that is not apt to be diminiſhed by a lingring diſeaſe? or any honour or grace which is not inpoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to be turned into diſhonor &amp; diſgrace? or what high riſing is there which is not apt to haue a dolefull downe fall? or is there any eſtate from the pedlar euen to the Prince, exempt from alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? and that which hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne to one may it not likewiſe befall vnto another? It were a matter both tedious, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our deſigne, to diſcourſe of ſuch as fortune (if ſo wee may ſpeake) from high roomes hath brought low, and of mighty men in a moment made miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. In ſuch a variety and viciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitude
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20501:30"/>
of matters, if ye doe not fore-bethink your ſelfe, how that all humane accidents may touch you, as wel as others, ye giue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities great power ouer you, the which by the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him that foreſeeth them are not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle abated, &amp; made more milde. Our minds out of queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhold be in greater reſt, if our actions were occupied about ſuch things as be of a more certain &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant condition. For at leaſt hauing once attained them, wee ſhould content our ſelues therwith, and enioy the ſweetnes and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity therof, in tranquility &amp; eaſe.</p>
               <p>But ſeeing that in this world, all things are ſubiect to totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and turning, and that there is nothing vnder the cope of heauen ſtable and firme: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy moſt fit vnto our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is to foreſee this inſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20501:30"/>
and not to paſſionate, and turmoyle our ſelues about thoſe things, the poſſeſſion whereof is no leſſe toyleſome, and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome then was the acquiſition &amp; purchaſe therof. And therfore wee muſt loue them as things which may leaue vs, and withall, we muſt haue ſo much foreſight that they neuer leaue vs the firſt. When on a time it was told <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxagoras</hi> that his ſonne was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed: I knew very well, quoth he, that he was a man, and that he was borne to dye once. In the like manner muſt we bee prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all aduentures. My friend hath not aſſiſted mee, well, I knew that he was a man, and one that might change. My wife was very vertuous, and yet was ſhe but a woman. The man that thus before hand bethinketh himſelfe of humaine accidents, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20501:31"/>
be taken at vnawares, neither ſhall he need to ſay, as cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the vnaduiſed are wont: I did not thinke of ſuch a thing: vnto whom the chances of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune do occaſion much affliction and anguiſh, becauſe they finde themſelues diſarmed of this wiſe foreſight. The well-aduiſed Prince in time of peace maketh ready his preparatiues for the time of warre. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> ouerpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many dangers and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and yet none of them all did afflict him ſo ſoare, as one thing which did take him at vnawares, euen the death of a dogge which hee loued deerely. So that the common prouerbe wee ſee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth true: <hi>That a perſon ſurpriſed is halfe beaten.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discourse">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20501:31"/>
               <head>DISC. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of each mans Vocation and Calling.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT cometh oftentimes to paſſe that ſuch as do not thinke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently of that which they doe, are ſeene to fall into ſuch a kind of life as is paineful to beare, and yet more vneaſy to be abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The which is certainely a great difficulty, and a caſe that doth require much prudence, and no leſſe patience, with piety to implore the aid and aſſiſtance of God; conſidering that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience with humility in Gods behalfe, is the remedy which moſt doth lighten and eaſe the euill. Conſider the poore pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, what paines they endure in the beginning to beare the burthen that is laid vpon their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20501:32"/>
legges, but after that they are once accuſtomed thereunto, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity teacheth them, and vſe maketh all ſuch hard vſage eaſie vnto them. There is no manner of life, howſoeuer hard &amp; ſtrict it be, which hath not ſome kinde of ſolace and refreſhment, one or other to ſweeten the ſame. And truly there is not any one thing, wherein Nature hath ſo much fauoured vs as in this; that ſhe maketh vs to finde the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and mittigation of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes in the ſufferance of the ſame.</p>
               <p>The caſe then ſo ſtanding as it doth, that man is borne obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſubiect vnto all manner of miſeries, we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe that wee are all of vs the priſoners of Fortune, who holdeth vs tyed, and fettered faſt hand and foote; and that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20501:32"/>
there is no difference, ſauing that the fetters and chaines of ſome, are of gold, and of other ſome of yron. We are all of vs in one &amp; the ſame priſon, and thoſe that hold others captiue are in the like condition and caſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in regard of others. If the deſire of honour turmoileth thee, the deſire of riches doth trouble another. If the baſeneſſe, and obſcurity of birth doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the, to others Nobility and greatneſſe doth bring a thouſand diſcontented thoughts: Art thou ſubiect to the commandement and will of another, that other is ſubiect at leaſt to his owne, hauing his braines and his breaſt beaten with ten thouſand heart-burnings, and diſeaſments which thou doeſt not eſpy, in ſumme if yee marke all things well, our whole life is nothing but a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20501:33"/>
wherein euery one ought to take good heed how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane himſelfe in his calling, &amp; how hee may content himſelfe therein, winking at that which is euill in it, and applying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto that which is good. For there is no calling, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer painefull and toylefull it bee, wherein the patient ſoule doth not finde ſome contentment and gaine, though that cunning and skill bee more exquiſite in time of aduerſity, then of proſperite. For when as difficulties and croſſes doe preſent themſelues, then muſt we gather all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our wits together, and ſet our whole vigour and vertue againſt ſuch imminent or preſent euils, repoſing our whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God. <hi>Ionas</hi> had euer leiſure within the Whales belly to make his ſupplication &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20501:33"/>
vnto God, and was preſently heard. In this manner all acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, howſoeuer grieuous and vneaſy they be, may be ſweetned and lightned not a little.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe alſo it is good that each one ſet certaine bounds and limits to the hopes of his life, and that hee thinke with himſelfe that howſoeuer humane things bee different and diuers for the outward ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and ſhew: that neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe inwardly they reſemble one another in their inconſtancy and vanity.</p>
               <p>Beare not enuy againſt ſuch as are in higher place then your ſelfe, for oftentimes that which we account height, is as a ſteepe hill from whence a man with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little adoe is hurled downe headlong. And truely ſuch as haue liued content, haue not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20501:34"/>
beene alwaies thoſe that haue made the better choiſe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe who prudently and diſcreetly could cary themſelues in that eſtate and calling which they once made choyce of, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king patiently the euill that fell out therein, and endeauouring to redreſſe ſuch accidents as did croſſe their deſires, and for this cauſe <hi>Plato</hi> did compare the life of man to the play at dice, wherat whoſeuer doth play, ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to ſtriue to haue a faire throwe, and yet ſhould content himſelfe with any caſt that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. For ſeeing that good or euill luck is not in our power, at leaſt wiſe wee muſt labour to take cheeerefully our chance, &amp; withall to thanke God, for that the worſt that could, is not fallen forth. Men of weake wit, hauing fortune at will, are ſo tranſported
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20501:34"/>
with ioy that ſcarcely they know what they doe, they are ſo inſolent, that no man can keepe them company, they can abide nobody and nobody can abide them. Whereas in the time of aduerſity they are ſo amaſed and ſo mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cholious, that they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ouerwhelmed with ſorrow and heauineſſe of mind, yee ſhall ſee them like vnto the ſicke of a languiſhing, and anguiſhing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, which can neither abide heat nor cold.</p>
               <p>The Philoſopher <hi>Theodorus</hi> was wont to ſay, that he gaue his Schollers inſtructions &amp; leſſons, with the right hand, but that they receiued them, with the left, and ſo doth it fare often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not with a few, who with the left hand take hold of the lucke which fortune (I meane Gods prouidence) reacheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20501:35"/>
with the right. It were much better in my iudgement wiſely to imitate the wiſe diligence of the Bees, the which of Thyme which is but a dry and harſh hearbe, do make the ſweete and pleaſant honey. So ſhould we out of this harſh and comberſome life ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and draw whatſoeuer ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is good, and in the meane time chaſe away what is euill therein, or caſe and couer it cloſly, and who knoweth not but that ſuch as are exerciſed in the actions of vertue can draw, by a certaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and ſupernaturall kind of alchimie, good out of euill? <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogenes</hi> was baniſhed, but hee made good vſe of his baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that he did in the meane time betake himſelfe vnto the ſtudy of wiſdome. And this ſhall not be ſo difficult and hard to do, as it ſeemeth to be, if by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20501:35"/>
freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exerciſe ye do endeauor to acquire, the habitude &amp; ſetled cuſtome of liuing content. Can ye not abide in the houſes of Princes and great men? content you then with your owne. Do ye find your ſelfe vncapable of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth? play then the good Citizens part &amp; be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to obey. Thus doing ye ſhall make vnto your ſelues facile, and eaſy, that which moſt men deeme to bee difficult and hard in the courſe of our life.</p>
               <p>Moreouer it ſhall much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile you in your diſcontentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to repreſent vnto your ſelfe the great and famous perſonages of the time paſt: how and with what wiſedome, and courage they haue remedied and borne the croſſes and calamities which befell them in this life, Doth it diſpleaſe you that you are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20501:36"/>
of children? Conſider how many Kings, Princes, and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, haue dyed without iſſue. If pouerty doth vexe you, weigh in your owne minde, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent men haue bene like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe poore, who neuertheleſſe haue liued patiently without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining. On a day it was told the Philoſopher <hi>Stilphon,</hi> that his daughter had done amiſſe: the fault (quoth he) is not in me, but in her fortune and mine. If the churliſh and froward conditions of your owne grieue you, ſet before your eyes ſo many wiſe, honourable and illuſtrious men, as haue quietly comported with the importunities of theirs. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> had the moſt froward wife in the world, and hee ſaid that, by enduring of her at home, hee did learne to bee patient abroad. Looke vpon holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20501:36"/>
a man after Gods owne heart, who yet was troubled and angred by his owne children.</p>
               <p>The world is full of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and if wee did not loue our ſelues ſo much as we doe, it is certaine that in the greateſt croſſes, &amp; enco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brements of this life, wee ſhould finde comfort enough. For there is not any priſon, how darke or ſtraight ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it bee, which will not giue place vnto a ſong, to refreſh ſomewhat the poore priſoners perplexed minde. Finally, I ſay, that if yee ſerue God and feare him, charity ſhall be able, of it ſelf, to procure peace &amp; tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity vnto your ſpirit: that which the whole world cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, although in word euery one ſhould offer you to doe the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="discourse">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:20501:37"/>
               <head>DISC. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How a man muſt order and rule his life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is expedient, in my conceit, that a man hold and keepe a certaine ſtaied and ſetled maner of liuing, and that he varie not not with euery winde. Ye ſhall ſee many a one much ſubiect to this vice of changing their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liuing from day to day; ſo that they cannot ground or ſettle themſelues vpon any thing whatſoeuer. Wherein they doe reſemble ſuch folks as haue euer beene accuſtomed to bee at ſea, who as ſoone as they beginne to ſaile, runne out of one veſſell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, leauing the bigger to put themſelues into a leſſer, and by &amp; by leauing the leſſer to returne to the bigger againe.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20501:37"/>
And thus they continue in chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, vntill at what time they know cleerely that nothing can fit them, becauſe that whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they goe, their queaſie ſtomackes doth keep them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and conſequently, their vomiting diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe thoſe that bring their paſſions with them vnto their affaires, do ſeeke inceſſantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a new manner of liuing, and neuer accompliſh what they haue once begun. All things go againſt their ſtomacke, all things diſpleaſe them, whether to bee imployed, or to be idle, to ſerue or to command, to be marryed, or to be ſingle, to haue children, or to haue none at all: finally; nothing doth fit their fancy, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth ſatisfie their deſire, ſaue onely that thing they haue not: and ſuch folke me thinkes
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20501:38"/>
muſt needs liue miſerably, and reſtleſly, as priſoners fettered in perpetuall paine.</p>
               <p>There is likewiſe another ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men not much vnlike vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the former, that cannot keepe themſelues quiet, nor bee at any ſtay, in any time, or in any place. They ceaſe not to go and come alwayes intermedling with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, without being thereunto called, and buſying and beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues about that which no wiſe concerneth them. Theſe men when they go out a doores, if yee but aske them whither they goe, they will anſwer you thus; <hi>I know not, I go to do as the reſt doe.</hi> They runne along the ſtreetes, they hant the publick places, and then they returne home full of vexation and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, without any deſigne: for there is nothing that doth ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20501:38"/>
much irke &amp; weary mens minds, as to labour in vaine. They are like vnto the little Ants, which do graſpe vpwards vpon trees, &amp; after they haue mounted vp to the top, haue but the paine to creepe downe againe, the ſame way they went vp, without brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging down with them any good at all. Many do liue in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, whoſe life is nothing els but a boyling leaſure full of tumults and toyles, yee ſhall ſee them poſting on with ſuch vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſpeede, as if they would carry away with them all that they finde before them in their way. The publicke places, the Churches, and Markets, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily full of ſuch folkes.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee they which forge, and frame newes at pleaſure: they will bee the weighers of mens worthes, and the giuers of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20501:39"/>
garlands. They will talke la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhly of other mens liues, and diſcourſe of other mens offices, keeping a babling coyle. But the actions of a wel-aduiſed man te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alwaies to ſome certain end; neither doth he burthen himſelfe with more buſineſſes then hee can conueniently put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And truely the man that vndertaketh much, muſt needes, in my minde, giue Fortune much power ouer him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the diuerſitie of Actions.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MEn, me thinketh, ought to take paines in inabling themſelues to comport with the time, and matters, according as they fall forth: and not to tye themſelues ſo much to one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liuing, but that in caſe of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20501:39"/>
neceſſity they may well leaue it. For euen as a man that is whole &amp; ſound, ſhould not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect himſelfe to the keeping of one certaine rule in his dyet, but ought rather to accuſtome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to eate ſomtimes more, and ſometimes leſſe, at one time of one meate, &amp; at another time of another meate; to drinke now of wine, and then of water, to ſtay ſometimes in the ſunne, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the ſhade, ſometimes to labour, and ſometimes to reſt: ſo muſt a man frame and faſhion himſelfe to all manner of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, for in ſo doing, any new accident whatſoeuer, that can befall you (for there falleth out an infinity of chances in the courſe of our life) ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor diſquiet you: yea though yee bee driuen to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelfe to ſome other
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20501:40"/>
maner of liuing, yet ſhall ye do it without much adoe (proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alwayes that temerity and raſhneſſe bee away) by reaſon that yee ſhall bee ſo well inured thereunto before hand, that it will bee eaſie for you to giue place vnto the time that offereth it ſelfe. And truly the impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and weakneſſe is all one, not to be able to change in time of need, and not to be able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue conſtant in a good courſe.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, wee muſt mingle and temper our matters in ſuch ſort that they may be fitted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably one to another. As for example. At one time to bee ſolitary, at another time to be in company, the one for our friends ſake, the other for our ſelues: for we muſt not alwaies remaine in our graue moode, for that ſhould make vs to be abhorred:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20501:40"/>
neither muſt we ſhew our ſelues continually iocund and glad, for that ſhould make vs to be deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But wee muſt carry our ſelues diſcreetly, obſeruing comelineſſe and conueniency of time and place, as the life of man doth require. For it is a needfull thing for a man at one time or other to recreate himſelfe, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing intermiſſion to his more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious affaires.</p>
               <p>We reade of <hi>Socrates,</hi> a moſt graue Phyloſopher, that he made no difficultie to play and refreſh himſelfe with the litle boies: and of <hi>Cato,</hi> a very auſtere man, that ſomtimes he did feaſt his friends, thereby to refreſh himſelfe with the pleaſure of their company, and to recreate his minde, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the weighty affaires of the Common-wealth. Alſo of <hi>Scipio Africanus,</hi> that ſometimes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20501:41"/>
he would delight himſelfe with daunſing.</p>
               <p>And this we haue ſaid to ſhew that the minde of man requireth ſome releaſe. Neither hath that man his due liberty, who hath not the meanes ſometimes to be at leaſure. The fruitfulleſt grounds, if they get not leaue to reſt a while, become barren in a ſhort time. Continuall labour maketh the minde of man to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſlacke and weake: euen as laſineſſe &amp; luxurie doth make it heauy, feeble, and faint. Our recreation ought to bee as our ſleepe, which reſtoreth our ſtrength, and giueth vs breath to returne more gayly, and ioyfully to our worke. For if we ſhould ſleepe continually, it ſhould bee a death and not a ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which of old did eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh lawes, haue ordained there
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20501:41"/>
ſhould bee alſo certaine feaſt-dayes in the yeare, to the end men might in a manner bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſurceaſe from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of their ordinary callings, and to take their paſtimes after their toyles: and of old we finde that many excellent men were wont to allot ſome parcell of time to their recreation. <hi>Aſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pollio</hi> a great Orator was neuer ſo much buſied in affaires, but hee reſerued for his pleaſure and paſtime the two laſt houres of the day; during the which ſpace, hee would not ſo much as reade the letters which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from his friends, fearing leſt they ſhould miniſter vnto him ſome new care and cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Others were wont to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vntill noone, and the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the day they did ſpend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout meaner matters. The lights
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20501:42"/>
which they diſtribute to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants at Court, doe like wiſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and bound the times appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both for labour and reſt.</p>
               <p>There was a decree of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of <hi>Rome,</hi> which did beare a prohibition that no new thing ſhould be propounded or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the laſt two houres of the day. Furthermore, when a man is wearie of his worke, hee doth finde himſelfe maruailouſly refreſhed and reſtored when as hee goeth out into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and ſpatious place, and it ſeemeth that the free aire doth repaire and renew the ſtrength and vigour of his diſpearſed and ſpent ſpirits. For concluſion, ye ought to loue diuerſity and change according to the time, and take heed leaſt yee nouriſh, and cheriſh your minde too de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately and daintely.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20501:42"/>For it hauing of the owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture great ſtrength, prouiding that it be wakened and rouzed vp, it were not reaſonable ye ſhould ſuffer it through volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and delitious liuing to waxe feeble and faint. And no ſooner do ye come to that point to be impatient and delicate, but as ſoone all things begin to croſſe your good liking. To eate it goeth againſt your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, to be hungrie it hurteth you, to ſleepe it ſlayeth you, to be awake it vexeth you: and as a ſicke or queaſie perſon, ye go on in a reſtleſſe maze, alwayes ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and ſeeking after ſome new thing: ſuch delicacie and tenderneſſe hath bene the cauſe that diuerſe haue had much ado to comport with the very things which are neceſſary in this life, as to lie, to ſleepe, to wake, to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20501:43"/>
riſe, to dine, to ſup, to talke, to walke, to cloath &amp; vncloath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſo that ſome haue thought it a death to be alwaies wearied in beginning a new againe &amp; ſo often the ſame things. Such folks come to ſuch extremities that hardly can they manage, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the manly courage of their minde; neither can they frame themſelues to all things, to know many things, to taſte of many things, and alwaies in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to carry a good ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke. For in this caſe there is the like reaſon and condition of the body and of the mind. Hence it is that ye ſhall eſpie ſome men ſo tenderly diſpoſed, that a ſmall noiſe of their neighbour will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy them, and the ſound of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bell will trouble their braine. For as vnto a craſie and ill-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexioned body, ſo vnto, a droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20501:43"/>
and languiſhing minde it doth ſemblably befall, that what thing ſoeuer toucheth it, doth pricke it and ſting it full ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the choice of friends.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SEeing that the life of man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily hath need of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and fellowſhip (for it were a matter both harſh and hard for a man to haue alwayes his mind bended about buſineſſe; and it ſhould be yet more weariſome if he had not one with whom he might take ſome releaſe) I finde that we proue commonly too negligent and careleſſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our choice. We ought in my iudgement to chuſe ſuch folkes for our friends as be of a mild and meeke conuerſation, and who becauſe of their calme
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20501:44"/>
and quiet diſpoſition do deſerue to be loued. Neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that ſo much doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, &amp; delight the mind of man, as doth a faithfull and truſtie friendſhip. For it is a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to find a perſon ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, vnto whom ye may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impart your moſt ſecret af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: whoſe counſell may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you, whoſe cheerfulneſſe may qualifie all your cares, and whoſe preſence may appeaſe all your paines, and expell your penſiueneſſe of mind: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye muſt endeauor to chuſe ſuch friends as are free from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, and all notorious vice. For vice like the fire taketh hold of that which is neereſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. So that we muſt doe as men are wont in the time of plague and peſtilence: which is to ſeparate and ſeuer the ſicke
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20501:44"/>
from the whole: it being a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion and an occaſion of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to let them liue together. Neuertheleſſe I do not like that we ſhould be in our choice too ſcrupulous, but ſeeing we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find folkes altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, wee muſt hold thoſe for good which be leſſe euill.</p>
               <p>But in the election of friends, ye ought chiefly to auoid ſuch as be extremely ſullen or ſad, who weepe and waile at all things: and diſpaire of all things, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>although otherwiſe they be ſuch as do loue you, and would proue faithfull inough vnto you. For it is a thing that muſt needs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs much to haue ſuch a man for our friend as is alwayes ſad, ſighing and ſobbing at euery oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. For ſeeing that friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and fellowſhip is ordained to driue away diſcontent, ſorrow
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20501:45"/>
and griefe, it were neither rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable nor conuenient to chuſe ſuch a one for your comforter and friend, as in ſtead of deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you, and of lightning your griefe, ſhould by his ſullenneſſe and ſadneſſe increaſe your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and euery day occaſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you ſome new vaine appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and feare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of diſſembling or diſguiſing of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is a great paine and a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe moleſtation of mind, for men to labour to appeare diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in ſhewe from that which they are in ſubſtance. And a marueilous trouble and torment it is for them to take alwayes heed vnto themſelues for the feare they haue to be diſcouered. Looke how often men looke on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20501:45"/>
them, as often doe they thinke that they are eſpied: ſo that in the end it falleth out that, nill they will they, they do bewray what humour and inclination doth beare rule in their breaſt. The exceſſiue care they haue to hide their naturall humor, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to an vnexplicable paine: and againe to be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered it putteth them to almoſt an intollerable ſhame. So that in this couered and masked kind of cariage there is not that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and eaſe, which is to be felt in the other plaine and ſimple kind of conuerſation that nature doth leade each man vnto. And though there be ſome little dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panying this plainneſſe that a man may be the leſſe eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of by the occaſion of this his inclination when it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cried: notwithſtanding in mine
<pb facs="tcp:20501:46"/>
opinion it were better for him to be a little leſſe accounted of, and to liue openly, then to haue ſuch a paine to diſguiſe himſelfe, and to carry himſelfe thus diſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. And yet in both the two there is to be kept a reaſonable mediocrity and meane: for there is a great difference betweene a franke and free faſhion of beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and a negligent, or care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe kind of cariage.</p>
               <p>To vnderſtand this point ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the better, we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how that nature hath indued man with two diuerſe qualities and properties: the one generall and common to vs all, in making vs reaſonable and capable of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, wherein we ſurpaſſe the bruit beaſts: the other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to each one of vs, as to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to grauitie, to policie, to melancholy, or to ſome ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20501:46"/>
In this euery one ſhould follow his naturall inclination, prouiding that it be not abſurde, vnſeemely, or vitious. As if a man bee ſubiect to too much laughter, it behoueth him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauor to amend this imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But in ſuch qualities, as are not blameable, it is good not to vſe counterfeiting, cloaking, or diſſembling. For it is a thing very vneaſie for that man alwaies to play the graue, who is not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally enclined to grauity, as to change his countenance, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large or raiſe ſwellingly his voyce, to faſhion and frame his eyes and lookes to auſteritie, maieſtie, and greatneſſe: The which geſtures if a man chance to forget through negligence and ouerſight, by and by he is diſcried.</p>
               <p>In my conceit it were much
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20501:47"/>
better for ſuch a man to follow his in-bred cheerfull inclination and gay humour in conuerſing with others.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, if it be a mans fortune to be preferred to a place of dignitie and honour, ſuch as doth require a graue, or ſeuere countenance and cariage, then in this caſe it behoueth him to conſtraine and commaund a little his iouiall inclination. But this muſt be done with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and moderation, and by degrees, and in ſuch ſort that this change offend no man. And this kind of diſſembling, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing of humours cannot be blamed; ſeing the quality of his charge doth require it, for the ſeemely bearing whereof, he muſt be content to take the paines to put aſide, or rather to ſmother a little of his facile and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20501:47"/>
eaſie diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>But there are ſome which being indeed light-headed and ridiculous, will notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that men take them for graue, ſtayed and magnanimous: and there are others againe, who without cauſe labour to counterfeit and couer, or rather ſmother their good inclination; for being borne of a mild and meeke diſpoſition, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor to daube themſelues ouer with the vntempered morter of inhumanitie, roughneſſe and auſteritie. And others there are who being very cowards, will yet make ſhew as if they were the moſt valorous in the world, and by no meanes can they be brought to know themſelues.</p>
               <p>But yet this their coloured &amp; conſtrained courage they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor carry farre off without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20501:48"/>
The common ſaying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes prouing true, <hi>That no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent or conſtrained thing hath any long continuance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="discourse">
               <head>DIS. 9.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is a thing very difficult, yea, I dare ſay impoſſible, that a vaine and ambitious man can euer attaine to taſte of this ſweet and moſt deſirable tranquility of minde, which the wiſe haue ſo diligently ſought for, by ſea and by land, on foote, and on horſe, ſparing no paines: for the man that hath his mind and heart eaten with the gnawing worm of ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cannot attain to that which he deſireth, to wit, that place, credit, and account, which he doth craue. And as of himſelfe hee promiſeth alwaies
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20501:48"/>
more then he can performe; ſo likewiſe in his habites, attire, and all his other things, he doth vſually goe beyond his meaſure. So that he is found to bee in the ſelfe ſame paine, wherin are lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all thoſe which ſtriue againſt the ſtreame, or which creepe and graſpe vpwards againſt a ſteepe brae, becauſe in ſetting forwards they make too much haſte, therefore it commeth to paſſe, that they doe lye the further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde. Contrariwiſe, the true meanes to attaine vnto eaſe is, for a man to make a ſmaller ſemblance &amp; ſhew then indeede his power and ability doth beare, and to ſet aſide all pompous ſuperfluity and vanity, as well in his attire, as in his traine: and to hold alwayes for his meaſure and rule that which is neceſſary, not that which hath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20501:49"/>
no other ground but a vaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or a friuolous conceite: yea in our very eating and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, we muſt take heed there appeare nothing ſo ſingular, or odde that men may in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner take notice thereof. It is likewiſe very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient and profitable, that we refraine our hopes, and that wee extend not our deſignes further then wee may well attaine vnto. As for riches, indeuour to come by them rather of your ſelfe, then of fortune: and euery way it is a principall point for a man to bee moderate as well in his actions as in his intentions. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, or ſtorme of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhall fal out, it ſhall haue the leſſer power to preuaile vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and to giue him the ouerthrow if it finde him with his ſailes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoyſed vp to</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="discourse">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:20501:49"/>
               <p>which ſuſtaine ſuch a ranke and dignity, that they cannot conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently debaſe themſelues, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they either fall from their place, or at leaſt, not cary them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the ſame as they ought. And ſuch men muſt imploy their prudence and wiſedome in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering their grauity, ſo that men may bee brought to impute it to their charge and calling, &amp; not to the naturall diſpoſition of their minde, and therefore it is good that they excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues towards their friends, and ſuch folkes as bee of a meaner ranke, whom they haue knowne fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly before, that they haue not the leaſure to entertaine them, &amp; to make much of them, by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> company, as otherwiſe they would very willingly doe: Yet ſo, that they vſe in the meane time, all the facilitie and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20501:50"/>
affability their condition &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling can ſuffer them to vſe; not bewraying or ſhewing any ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or angry moode, by their viſage or words, if a man chance to come to them at an vnſet houre, or yet ſpeake to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more importunatly, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreetly then reaſon would require. For it is a like vice for a man not to know how to carry himſelfe in his proſperity, and not to bee able to comport with aduerſitie: we ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to obſerue an equalitie in our whole life, and to ſhewe alwaies (if it be poſſible) In all the changes and chances thereof one and the ſame countenance, full of courteſie, mildneſſe, and gentle in behauour. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great did farre outrunne his father <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> by his high and excellent
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20501:50"/>
feates of warre: but his father did farre ſurmount him in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and gentleneſſe of mind. The Father was alwaies vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and welbeloued, but the ſonne was oftentimes vitious &amp; hated: In ſuch ſort that there counſell is queſtionleſſe whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſound, which tell vs that the higher and loftier men are, the humbler and lowlier ought they to be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> was wont to ſay, that euen as men are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to put wilde and vntamed horſes into the hands of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers and Riders, that beeing daunted and tamed they may ſerue them in their turnes. So likewiſe is it needfull to tame proud and inſolent perſons, that haue growne wild through the aboundance of fortunes fauour, and to bring them againe within
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20501:51"/>
the round and compaſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by ſetting before their eye the wretchedneſſe and weakenes of humane matters, and the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability and inſtability of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. And for this end we ought in our greateſt proſperity to vſe the aduiſe and counſell of our friends, yea, then we ſhould giue them more authority and power ouer vs then at any other time to the end they may be the more bold towards vs in telling vs the truth. We muſt alſo ſtoppe our eares to flatterers, which may very eaſily beguile vs: For at all times men do deeme &amp; eſteeme themſelues, to be ſuch, as ought to bee praiſed and raiſed to the skies, but moſt of all in time of proſperity: In the which it is a thing very rare and difficult to find a man who doth not incline to attribute vnto himſelfe the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20501:51"/>
cauſe of his owne good happe. Neither is there any other ſeaſon in the which men more eaſily forget God, then that when as they enioy health and wealth, dgnity and felicity according to their wiſh. In manner that miſhap whenſoeuer it doth hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them, doth ſerue them for a medicine, becauſe it bringeth them home againe vnto the knowledge of themſelues.</p>
               <p>This opinion of ſelfe-conceit for a man to thinke too much of himſelfe, and to giue credite lightly vnto the fawning lyes of flatterers, maketh men to ſtumble, yea to fall into many groſſe faultes, yea giueth occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mocking and ſcoffing them bitterly, and out of all peraduenture it is a great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, yea a fond folly for a man to relye more vpon anothers
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20501:52"/>
iudgement concerning himſelfe, then vpon his owne.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Phillip</hi> (of whom wee ſpake before) ſeeing himſelfe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mighty and victorious, and conſidering with himſelfe, as a wiſe and moderate man ought to doe, how that humane things do not alwaies abide in the ſame ſtay, appointed that one of his pages ſhould haue no other thing elſe to do euery day, but only each morning to ſalute him with theſe words. <hi>Phillip, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou art a mortall man.</hi> But how much more may the wiſe and wel-diſpoſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſay euery day to himſelfe; <hi>Remember that thou art earth, and to earth thou muſt returne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="discourse">
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:52"/>
               <head>DISC. 11.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the comparing of our fortune with that of others.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is much auaileable for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of this tranquility of minde, that a man ſetting aſide all paſſions, conſider with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe what meanes and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites he doth enioy, and in the next place that he ſet before his eyes ſuch men as haue not ſo much: not doing as many are wont, who haue their eyes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon ſuch as ſurpaſſe them, as admiring them, and reputing them onely happy and bleſſed. The priſoners hold them happy that are ſet at large; and againe, thoſe eſteeme ſuch bleſſed as are altogether free. The free thinke the rich onely fortunate, and the rich againe thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<pb facs="tcp:20501:53"/>
They that command ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Kings of all other moſt bleſſed, and Kings thoſe of their degree that excell them in abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and power, hence it is that men finding themſelues vnable to equall ſuch as ſurpaſſe them, they doe remaine diſcontented and no wiſe ſatisfied with their fortune, wherein they both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray their ingratitude towards God, and beget a torment to themſelues. A wiſe man will not bee malcontent, though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſurmount him in meanes, but rather repreſenting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the great numbers of afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and miſerable men the world doth affoord, hee will reioyce &amp; be glad of his condition &amp; caſe. If ye ſee then a man well moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and furniſhed with faire hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, richly arayed, doe but caſt downe a little your eyes and
<pb facs="tcp:20501:53"/>
conſider how many there are that go a foote, which, leading a poore life, eſteeme that of yours to be happy, for it is not reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable that the good fortune of one, or of a few, ſhould haue greater force to make you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, then ſhould the bad for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of many haue to moue you to be content. How many poore folkes ſee ye dayly, that liue of their labours, &amp; are laden with children, and pinched with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, and which is worſt of all, haue no hope at all to eſcape out of their miſery? How many is there to whom your life, which ye ſo much deplore, would bring much conſolation and eaſe?</p>
               <p>Wee are come vnto a time ſo miſerable, that one mans life de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth more of anothers then of it ſelfe: and the good of our neighbour doth occaſion vs
<pb facs="tcp:20501:54"/>
greater greife then is the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we reape of our owne. But if it were poſſible for men to ſee vnfolded the fortune of ſuch as they eſteeme happy, they ſhould feele and find in it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more anxiety and paine, then they do in their owne. Who is hee that doth not account the condition of Kings of all other to be moſt happy? And yet harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what a great King ſaith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in <hi>Homer: Great Iupiter hath impriſoned mee, with great perplexities and cares.</hi> O how happy then are thoſe that liue in their little corners out of theſe dangers and feares! And if it bee ſo that ten thouſand folkes would be content with the eſtate wherein God hath eſtabliſhed you, what reaſon haue you to complaine, for that yee haue not the eſtate and fortune of one
<pb facs="tcp:20501:54"/>
whom yee enuy? Yee haue no cauſe at all to ſlay your ſelfe with ſorrow and care, for to attaine vnto another mans ranke, ſeeing there is nothing, that ſo much troubleth and tormenteth a man as this affection &amp; immoderate deſire of mounting from one degree of dignity to another. For ſuch folkes ordinarily doe follow without conſideration any hope whatſoeuer that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it ſelfe; the which if it faile to ſucceede according to their wiſh, they preſently begin to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe fortune, and to accurſe their hap; whereas they ought rather to blame themſelues for their raſhneſſe and lightneſſe, and their want of foreſight, Neither do they conſider what a folly it is for them, to impute vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the blame of their owne weake vnderſtanding, and the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20501:55"/>
fault they haue fallen into by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that which was either vncertaine, or impoſſible for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to attaine vnto. They are like vnto thoſe, in my conceit, which fret and fume for that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not flye, or ſhoote an arrow with a bow as big as a plow beame.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of this euill is the exceſſiue affection men beare vnto themſelues: whence it commeth to paſſe, that in all things they will needs ſtriue to be the firſt. It is nothing in their eye to haue wealth, except they haue much more then other rich men haue.</p>
               <p>Behold how this vice reigneth, or rather rangeth in all eſtates. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the firſt was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be King of <hi>Sicile,</hi> neither eſteemed he his dignity accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed inough, becauſe <hi>Philoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> did ſurpaſſe him in poëſie,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20501:55"/>
and <hi>Plato</hi> in philoſophy. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he fell into ſuch a fury, that hee condemned <hi>Philoxenus</hi> to the quarries, there to wring ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of the hard rockes, and baniſhed <hi>Plato</hi> out of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</p>
               <p>And out of this immoderate loue it doth alſo proceede, that men will ſpeake of all things, thereby to ſhew that they know all things: whereby they make themſelues oftentimes to bee mocked at, as it once happened to <hi>Megabyſes</hi> the Perſian, a man otherwiſe of great reputation, and valour, who hauing vpon a time entred into the lodging where the famous painter <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> did plye and practiſe his art, began to diſcourſe touching the ſame, and would needes giue him to vnderſtand, that hee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the nature and ſecrets
<pb facs="tcp:20501:56"/>
thereof. To whom <hi>Apelles,</hi> as being a man wiſe, and well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned, thus anſwered: Truly, ſir <hi>Megabyſes,</hi> before I heard you ſpeake, I held you for a diſcreete man, for your ſilence did grace your braue apparell, but ſince yee haue medled to talke of my trade, truſt me, there is not euen vnill the ſmalleſt boy here that doth bray the okre, but will mocke you for your labour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hanniball,</hi> that great Captaine of <hi>Carthage,</hi> after that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> had chaſed him out of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly</hi> &amp; <hi>Affricke,</hi> fled towards the king of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> where, on a day, hee was inuited to goe into the Schooles, to heare a great Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher diſcourſing of the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemes, trickes, and ſubtilties of warre: his auditors wondring at his eloquence and ſcience of the military Art, asked of <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:20501:56"/>
what he thought of him; who laughingly anſwered them: That hee had knowne many old fooles, but that hee had neuer ſeen, nor heard any man vttering ſo many fond and fooliſh words as that man did, whom they all ſo much admired. And not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe did he anſwer them in this wiſe: conſidering how that this man did take vpon him to diſcourſe largely and lauiſhly of a matter, which very hardly can be taught or learned in the ſhade of a Schoole, and that in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and audience of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Captaine, and moſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented wariour that was then in the whole world. Which may teach euerie man to containe himſelfe within the compaſſe of his calling, without medling or troubling himſelfe with that of another mans. The which thing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20501:57"/>
the Poets alſo haue giuen vs to vnderſtand, when as they faine that their gods do content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues each one with his owne calling and charge. <hi>Mars</hi> med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with warre, <hi>Minerua</hi> with arts, <hi>Mercurius</hi> with eloquence, <hi>Cupido</hi> with loue, <hi>Neptunus</hi> with the Sea, <hi>Pluto</hi> with hell, <hi>Iupiter</hi> with the heauens, and ſo of the reſt, each one keeping himſelfe within the bounds and liſts of his vocation. And if it had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that any of them ſhould haue encroched vpon the office and function of another, hee ſhould not haue miſſed to bee ſcoffed and chaſtiſed for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
               <p>Hence wee may gather, that all things doe not befit, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all men, and that each one ought to conſider what calling he findeth himſelfe moſt apt and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20501:57"/>
ſufficient for, and that hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent him therewith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine himſelfe therein. They that follow the profeſſion of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and learning, haue neede of leaſure and eaſe. Hee that will follow the Court, and laboureth to haue the countenance and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of great men, and to finde acceſſe vnto Princes, muſt needs vndergo much pains. So that theſe conditions, and the like, are not fitting for all: and it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth each one vpon to know whereunto he is moſt apt. The Horſe is fit for riding &amp; ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning: the Oxe for opening &amp; laboring the ground. The man that would be ſory for that he cannot beare a lyon in his boſome, as he could a little dogge, were he not more then madde?</p>
               <p>There are ſome, who without leauing any part of their eaſe,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20501:58"/>
and of their vice, would bee as wiſe as the Phyloſophers that haue both day and night ſtudied and trauelled ſo much. The good wreſtlers of old contenting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their prize, ſuffered the other Champions to winne likewiſe theirs at running. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe ſuch as deſpiſing and diſdaining their owne good, do ſighingly ſeeke after another mans, do they not liue in diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and paine?</p>
               <p>They ſay, that in times paſt, there was a notable kinde of men in <hi>Baeotia,</hi> which did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of their gods becauſe that their figge trees did not beare grapes, and that their vines did not bring forth figges. Wee muſt imagine that God hath fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned &amp; framed diuerſly men for diuers affairs, &amp; that each one ought to content himſelfe with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20501:58"/>
that ability or place which God hath imparted vnto him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſing beyond his owne, to purſue, and follow after that which is anothers. For this kind of people make none account at all of that which they haue, but onely of that which they would haue: they go alwaies looking a farre off, and little thinke of the place wherein they are.</p>
               <p>There was of old, in a certaine Temple, an image pourtraied, which did repreſent the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, that alwayes wait on the time to come, and neglect the good oportunity of the time preſent. The picture was of a Rope-maker who did ſtill work, but ſuffered an Aſſe that ſtood behinde him to eate vp his worke. And thus do the ingrate people in Gods behalfe, who making no reckoning of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20501:59"/>
goods they enioy, ſuffer them to be buried in obliuion, and are alwaies couetous of things to come. In the harmony of the world, the differences, or diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to bee obſerued: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in humane things, all are not of one ſort. And as in muſick there are tunes and ſounds, ſome graue, ſome ſharpe, and ſome meane, of the mingling whereof the skilfull Muſitian maketh a ſweete melodie: ſo doth the prudent man make an harmony of the good &amp; euill that occurre in this life, not taking the good or the euill alone, but conſorting and tempering the one with the other, as things which in this world can neuer bee fully ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. That faire prouerbe vttered by <hi>Eurypides,</hi> but vſed of all, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing true: <hi>That ſorrow and mans life are ſiſters of one wombe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="discourse">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:20501:59"/>
               <head>DISC. 12.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Aduerſity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ADuerſity is of it owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture grieuous and heauy vnto our hearts, as ſickeneſſe, the loſſe of children, or of friends, with ſuch like other diſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents. But yet in part wee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the popular opinion in the apprehenſion thereof, and this we doe principally in our owne wants, and in the neceſſities of ours, as alſo in the matter of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, circumuentions and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, and when as we imagine that the honour is not deferred vs which we do deſerue.</p>
               <p>And againſt theſe croſſes of the ſecond kind, mee thinketh it were good for vs to apply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues the ſaying of the Poet <hi>Menander, That which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20501:60"/>
hath befallen you, is not indeed grieuous, but onely it ſeemeth to you ſo,</hi> and that it is ſo, it may appeare in that ye haue your minde and body as much at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement as yee had before the croſſe did befall you. And againſt the croſſes of the firſt kind yee ought to conſider how that ye endure nothing contrary to the lawe and courſe of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, in regard that all theſe accidents are annexed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mans being, and that from his birth they are allotted to him for ordinary: and the truth is that nature hath not framed vs ſo feeble, to beare out aduerſity, as we make our ſelues to be. Let vs rather alwaies thinke, that it is but our inferiour part which is ſubiect vnto fortune, &amp; that we haue the principall in our owne power: and that that which ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20501:60"/>
in vs, as concerning vertue, cannot bee ouercome by any other thing elſe, without our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment: alſo we know that we haue not need of any great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the doing hereof; wee hauing none to fight againſt but our owne ſelues, and ſeeing that the better part of the victory conſiſteth in maiſtering of our owne will: whereunto adde this, that God will alwaies fauour the man who through the ayde of rectified reaſon diſpoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the ſtronger. Fortune (if ſo it be lawful for a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeak) may wel make thee poore, abaſe thee, &amp; afflict thee, but ſhe is not able to make thee vitious, laſie, or ill-conditioned, neither can ſhe bereaue thee of the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage &amp; vigor of minde, wherein doth lye greater ſtrength to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne thy ſoule, then there is in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20501:61"/>
the Art of Nauigation to direct a ſhip. For the Marriner, let him be neuer ſo skilfull and wiſe in his Art, cannot with all his skill aſſwage the ſurging tempeſt of the Sea, nor yet take away feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full apprehenſions from another mans fantaſie. Whereas vertue and wiſedome in a well ordered minde doth aſſure and ſettle the body, for it preſerueth it from diſeaſes through temperance, &amp; pulleth it backe from wicked and vitious diſpoſitions by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and whereas any thing, wherin there is danger, ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelfe vnto our minde (as if it were in a dangerous ſhoare) it is good that wee leaue it and paſſe further: or elſe if the euill be vnauoydable, let him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe, and thinke with himſelfe that the hauen is not very farre off: and that his ſoule
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20501:61"/>
goeth out of the body, as out of a craſy or broken barke, holding death for a ſweete and aſſured harbour, chiefly conſidering that in regard of the nature of the ſoule, her out-going from this life, is her in-going to a better. The which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought to adde much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the courage of Chriſtians, Yea, and make them not to feare that which bringeth afrightme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto others, And truely if wee had skill and courage enough, to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the blowes of froward fortune, to looke her in the face, and to meete her in the way with a ſtoute ſtomack, prepared to ſuſtaine all her aſſaults, nothing in the world could diſmay vs, or yet put vs to paine. And this thing ſhould certainely come to paſſe, if we could once bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed neuer to promiſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20501:62"/>
to our ſelues any great or aſſured hopes, or yet any certaine and ſettled eſtate, during this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life, and if wee would take heed diligently, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe things we do account as euill, be ſo euill as we deeme them to be, or if happely they be not ſo euill but rather leſſe then wee imagine. Finally this thing ſhould come to paſſe if we would behold a farre off, and wiſely foreſee frowning fortune, for in ſo doing we might aſſure our ſelues, that at her comming ſhe ſhould not afright vs, but the neerer ſhee came to vs, the bolder wee might bee to looke her in the face, and to eſteeme her not to be ſo luſty and ſtrong as her picture would import, and if no man bee able to boaſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this life, ſo farre as to ſay, I am exempted from this bitter
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20501:62"/>
potion, at leaſt may he ſay thus, though I muſt ſwallow it down, yet ſhall I not be agaſt, weepe and waile I will not, neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire as many men do. I will not bring my ſelfe into ſo deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a plight as diuers do, amidſt their diſaſters. Though pouerty pinch me more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many others, for all that: wil I not beguile my neighbour, nor yet take that to my ſelfe, which to another doth belong: I will not lie, much leſſe will I forſweare my ſelfe. Breefly there ſhall nothing vnto me ſeeme ſo intollerable, as that for to ſhunne it, I would chooſe to become vitious. If by honeſt meanes I cannot auoide indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and need, at leaſt neceſſity ſhall make this neceſſity of mine eaſy to bee borne. Beſides that the common law of humane things, doth not allow vs to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20501:63"/>
eſteeme that thing heauy and vnbeareable, which ſo many dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe carry and beare on their backes: for chooſe what manner of afflictions yee will, yee ſhall finde more men burthened therewith, then exempted there-from.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt likewiſe comfort our ſelues with this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that where there is no ſinne, there can be no true euill at all: and that the vertuous man is more calme and quiet in his dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt aduerſity, then is the vitious man in his higheſt proſperity, &amp; ſuch were the croſſes of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men of old, which by the help of the diuine grace, were ſo accompanied with fortitude, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and humility, that how-ſharpe and rough ſoeuer they were, yet they brought them not ſo much vexation and anguiſh as
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20501:63"/>
their conſcience did them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and eaſe, and euen as thoſe that are ſicke of a feuer, feele ſooner and in more paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner, the heate and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their fit, then doe the whole and ſound the ſharpeſt cold of Winter, or the ſcorching heate of Summer: ſo likewiſe doth it fare, with thoſe that are troubled with the feuer of their vitious affections, the which do burne and bliſter extremely and continually their conſcience: for they are much more vexed with the corrupt and vitious qualities they do beget and beare in their boſomes, then are vertuous men with all their aduerſities. For theſe hauing the inward and better part ſound and without wound, cannot bee hurt by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accidents, whereunto they oppoſe a liuely and luſty courage
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20501:64"/>
together with the force of an honeſt and inuiolable mind, which is a ſtronger force (truely) then any whatſoeuer elſe. Think not that riches, howſoeuer abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant they be, cannot affoord ſo great contentment to the owner thereof, as vertue doth vnto the vertuous man, the which is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make him content: For vertue in whomſoeuer it be, is alwaies the reward and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe of her ſelfe. And euen as the moſt precious plants, &amp; ſweet-ſmelling trees, though they be cut in peeces and dryed, keepe alwaies their ſweete and pleaſing ſent, when as the vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoury and barren doe not pleaſe the ſenſe, euen then when they are whole and full of bloſſomes and floures: euen ſo the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man in the very midſt of his aduerſity reapeth more pleaſure
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20501:64"/>
and contentment of his vertue, and honeſty, then the vitious can do of his wealth and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity, being beaten and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with a curſed conſcience. In one word, in what time, place, or condition ſoeuer ye finde the vertuous man, ye ſhall finde him alwaies content.</p>
               <p>It is reported that <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Philoſopher, ſeeing, on a time, a certaine man dreſſing and dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelfe for a Feſtiuall day, ſaid vnto him thus: <hi>Why doeſt thou take ſuch paines to trimme thy ſelfe to day, conſidering that euery day is a festiuall day to the vertuous man?</hi> And truly euery day of the life of the vertuous man is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne day, and fit for a moderate reioyſing and mirth. For if wee looke well vnto the matter, the world is no other thing elſe but a faire and holy Temple, into
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20501:65"/>
the which a man is broght to ſo ſoone as he is borne: and within this Temple there is to be ſeene two bright Lampes, or Torches ſet vp, the Sunne &amp; the Moone, with many other ſtarrie lights. There may wee ſee and behold diuers kinds of creatures, by the meanes whereof Man attaineth to the knowledge of other eſſences, that cannot bee ſeene. What a ſweete ſight is it to ſee ſo many faire floods, and cleare running riuers, which ſend out alwayes freſh water; to ſee ſo many fruitfull, and flouriſhing Trees, plants, hearbes, and roots: the beautifull variety of beaſts, and of ſtones, together with the graſſie hils, and high mountaines on the one hand, and the low valleyes, and pleaſant plaines on the other? If man were ſo wiſe as hee ſhould be, this ſame ſight
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:20501:65"/>
and ſhew might ſerue him for a paſſe-time, and a play. For what thing is there in this life more worthy to bee ſeene then the paſſe-times and pleaſures which God doth affoord and offer vs in his creatures, if we could vſe the ſame as we ought? Why doe we take greater delight in any artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſport of beaſts, then we do to behold them acting the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of natures play, each kinde of them their owne part, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this faire &amp; wide ſtage of the world? Or is there any muſicke ſweeter then the chirping and ſinging of birds? In ſumme, it is a great delectation to ſee &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the diuerſity of creatures which God hath framed &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med each one to his kind: we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d away our life about ſo many purpoſes &amp; practiſes, ſo many toils &amp; broiles, that hardly
<pb facs="tcp:20501:66"/>
wee doe enioy any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and yet for all that we leaue not to enioy the other good creatures of God. If a man could once attain to this point of perfection, as to rid his mind out of theſe manifold entangleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and to giue it ſome ſpace &amp; place to entertaine, cheriſh, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it ſelfe with the knowledge of the creatures, and of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Creator, nothing ſhould, or could, caſt it into any exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſorrow, except it were ſinne, for the ſoule being once vnited with him that made it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and meditation, by knowledge and loue, it ſhould gather it ſelfe together calmely and quietly, ſo that a man ſhould lead and liue continually a glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life, conſidering that at one time or other ſome euill hath befallen him; yet oftener hath he
<pb facs="tcp:20501:66"/>
taſted of good. So that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as it were, the one with the other, hee may well ſay that hee hath greater occaſion to reioyce of his good ſucceſſe, then to complaine of the euill aduenture of another time, as wee are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to turne our eyes away from ſuch things as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, and to caſt them vpon greene, and gay colours that pleaſe vs: ſo ſhould wee diuert thee yes of our vnderſtanding, together with our thoughts, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſad and ſorrowfull obiects, and apply them to ſuch as are more pleaſing and agreeable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, neither muſt we be like vnto the malitious man, who behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth another mans faultes with the eies of an Eagle, but his own with the eyes of an owle. But our peruerſnes is ſuch, that very often we doe reſemble the box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſes,
<pb facs="tcp:20501:67"/>
which draw and drinke vp the corrupt bloud, and leaue the pure and cleane bloud behind. There was in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, a certain rich wretch, who had in his houſe great ſtore of wine; but yet was ſo nigar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh and neare, that hee ſold the beſt, and kept the worſt for his owne vſe: a certaine ſeruant of his, obſeruing this pinching and prepoſterous nigardlines of his maiſter, fled away from him: and being asked afterwards, why he had left his Lord anſwered thus: <hi>Becauſe I could not endure to ſtay with a man, who hauing that which was good, made choiſe of that which was euill.</hi> The Philoſopher <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtippus,</hi> made yet a farre better reply, who hauing loſt one of his three Farmes, ſaid thus vnto his friends, <hi>That it was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhnes to bee ſory, for one Farme
<pb facs="tcp:20501:67"/>
loſt, and not to bee merry for the other two that did reſt in his hands, ſeeing that all of them had lyen open to the ſame aduenture.</hi> We are like vnto little children, from whom, if ye pull but one of their playockes and knackes, they wil preſently, without more ado, fling away all the reſt in deſpite. For if, of many good things that we enioy, it chance that one of them, either be taken from vs, or that it be loſt, by and by we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to bewaile it, forgetting all that reſteth behind in our hands.</p>
               <p>But ſome man bewailingly will aske me, ſaying: alas! what haue we? to whom askingly I would anſwere: But what rather haue we not? One hath great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and credite, another hath wealth, and another health, one hath a wife according to his
<pb facs="tcp:20501:68"/>
wiſh and will, another hath ſweete children, and another faithfull and truſty friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> of <hi>Thraſe</hi> did rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it among his other good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, that he had ſailed proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly betweene <hi>Sicile</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> and wee each one of vs would haue all, though we haue not in the meane time the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to thanke God, for the ſmalleſt thing. Neither make wee any account or reckoning of the greateſt goods becauſe they ſeeme to vs to bee too common, as to liue, to be in health, to ſee, to heare, to ſpeak, to enioy peace, to eate and drink, to haue foode for our belly, &amp; clothes for our back, to ſee &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the fruites of the labourable ground, together with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of the ſaileable ſea, that we can talk, or hold our tongue,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20501:68"/>
ſit, or ſtand, ſleepe or wake as we will. If men would but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in their mindes, what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and griefe redoundeth vnto ſuch as doe lacke any of theſe abilities, they would, no doubt, liue much more content then they do. What thinke yee would the ſicke giue for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of health? the blind for the vſe of his eyes? and ſuch as are deſpiſed for a ſmall meaſure of renowne? wee wretches are ſo blockiſh and blind, that wee can neuer prize the goods that we haue, vntill that we be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of them, and haue them no more.</p>
               <p>That which reſteth, I wiſh you alwaies to bee aduertiſed that ye fall neuer ſo farre in loue with the things of this life, that the feare ye haue to looſe them vexe you with vnreſt, or yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:20501:69"/>
loſt them, immoderate ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them hurle you head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into diſpaire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 13.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of ſadneſſe, and ſorrow.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ADuerſity doth beget in vs vexation and griefe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the greatneſſe or ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: whereabout like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there happeneth ſome fault: for now a daies we may ſee men, ordinarily, mourning and moaning exceſſiuely for many things, not ſo much for that they haue cauſe, as becauſe it is the cuſtome. One lamenteth the miſhaps of his neighbour, or friend, and carrieth a pale and heauy countenance, to ſhew that hee is very ſorry therefore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee bee nothing ſorry at all. This kinde of cuſtomable
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:20501:69"/>
compaſſion is altogether vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, in regard that euen in your owne aduerſity, yee ought not to be ſad, but onely ſo farre forth as reaſon doth require, and not as cuſtome doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, How many is there who weepe when others looke on them, and do thinke it ſhould be a very ill fauoured thing, not to ſhed teares when as others do, mourne? How many friuolous ſorrowes hath it made many to ſlide into, to leane too much vpon the tottering and vnſtayed proppe of opinion? How much better were it in ſuch caſes, to deuiſe ſome new faſhion, and to feele humane accidents after that moode which beſt becommeth wiſe and moderate men? What good do their immoderate ſighs and ſobs, either to the liuing or to the dead? Doth their any
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:20501:70"/>
ther thing flow therfro, ſaue that they waſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues wretchedly &amp; wretchleſly away? For though it be true that oftentimes ſuch diſaſters and accidents fall out, that it is impoſſible for men to paſſe them ouer without being touched with ſorrow for the ſame: neuertheles wee muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beware to bee more ſorry then reaſon doth allow, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that time ought to heale you in the end, it were a babiſhneſſe not to preuent it wiſely, and to doe that betimes, which once at laſt, nill we will we, it behooueth vs to doe.</p>
               <p>How many men, ſhortly after the death of their children, or wiues, haue recomforted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as eſteeming the time loſt which they had ſpent in ſadneſſe and in ſorrow? For although it bee true, that ſuch perſons are
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:20501:70"/>
worthy to bee renewed in our remembrance, yet wee ought to bring thereunto that modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and remedy, which at laſt wil needs offer and apply it ſelfe, though ye would neuer ſo faine it were otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 14.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the affliction of good men.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is not a ſmall occaſion of ſorrow vnto vigorous minds, and ſuch as are touched with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity to ſee vertuous men vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended or wronged: and truly it ſeemeth to be nothing leſſe then a heauy heart-break &amp; almoſt an vnſupportable paine to behold wiſe &amp; peaceable men afflicted, troubled, and vexed, yea to bee ill-vſed, &amp; trampled, as it were, vnder feete by the vaine world, and to ſay the truth, it ſeemeth
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:20501:71"/>
that this doth touch vs very neere: for when as wee weigh with our ſelues that the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and lot of vertuous men is no other but affliction, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of minde, we do therupon preſently imagine, that thereby our beſt hopes are hemmed in.</p>
               <p>If then ſuch a caſe diſquiet you, (as ordinarily it doth) thinke with your ſelfe, that if they be honeſt and patient men then are they in that caſe ſo much the more happy, becauſe that in this life, which is ſo ſhort, they purchaſe to themſelues a life eternall in the heauens, for ye muſt know that the firſt good which ſuch as go to reſt in Gods houſe do obtaine, is to be quit and diſcharged from the tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and torments of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:20501:71"/>Moreouer, ſet before your eyes the roll and ſcroll of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men of old, the bleſſed Martyrs of Chriſt, of whom ſome haue beene beheaded, others haue beene hanged; ſome haue beene burnt, and others haue beene broyled; ſome haue beene cut in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and others haue had their skinne pulled off. Beſides that, during their life they haue beene afflicted with hunger, nakednes, and neede: of whom certainly the world was not worthy, and therfore it had them in horrour, as thoſe in whom it had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt at all. But God loued them deerely, and by his diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, which cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, appointed them to paſſe through ſuch tribulations, as through a needles eie, into the place of perpetuall repoſe. Yea
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:20501:72"/>
the paines and perplexities that vertuous men do endure, do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen pricke them forwards to haue a more earneſt deſire to loath, and to leaue this wretched world. So that in the end they diſlodge out of a bad &amp; ſad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they eſcape &amp; ſlip out of the dark caues and obſcure corners, and hauing no deepe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of death, they finde the faire beaten way that leadeth them to a better life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 15.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of other mens faults and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AFter that yee haue thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of your ſelfe, and haue appeaſed your owne paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet ſhall yee haue the vices of others, and the faults which are done in publicke, making an
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:20501:72"/>
on-ſet againſt you, to trouble your minde. Conſidering the diſorder that is amongſt men; which is ſo great, that ſcarcely can any thing bee found in the roome where it ought to be, and that there is ſcarcely any one that doth the duty whereunto by birth and calling hee was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The man who ſhould proue the wiſe Iudge, is a ſimple Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen: and he that ought to be but a meere citizen, is made a Iudge, and that man doth command who ought to obey.</p>
               <p>It is a ſtrange thing to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how that almoſt euery thing is corrupt and ſold, &amp; how that, as it were, all things are turned vpſide downe. To ſee how that the poore man is puniſhed for euery petty treſpaſſe, &amp; the pui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and wealthy perſon is ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: to ſee, I ſay, how the whole
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:20501:73"/>
plotting and plodding of men now a daies, is altogether for money.</p>
               <p>Againe, it cannot but bring griefe vnto a good mans minde, to conſider how ſmall occaſion and example of liuing vertuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch perſons do miniſter vnto vs, as hold the chiefe offices and the firſt rankes in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. The vertuous man is holden euery where as a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, abhorred, diſpiſed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. And what ſhall a man ſay, when as hee weigheth with himſelfe the variable &amp; mutable diſpoſition of the multitude, one while louing, and another while loathing, at one time praiſing, at another time diſpraiſing one and the ſame thing, one and the ſame party? How many bee the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable changes that fall out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men? And what a hard
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:20501:73"/>
caſe is it, when men make none account of that they ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently heare: and on the other ſide hearken to that whereunto they ſhould rather ſtop the eare? The diſpite and diſlike that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue conceiued, by reaſon of ſuch courſes, hath made them bid the world farewell, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the deſerts and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie aboades, as not being able to behold with their eyes, that which did breede, and bring ſo much diſpleaſure to their minds. And therefore ſuch haue choſen to liue rather amongſt the wilde beaſts, amidſt the vaſte wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and rocky mountaines, then amongſt ſo many wild men, ſwarming with vile and wicked manners.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe, in theſe, and ſuch other occurrents as cannot
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:20501:74"/>
bee amended, man muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and maiſter his minde, and carry himſelfe in ſuch ſort, that theſe vnamendable euils make him not to abhorre the company and ſociety of men: but rather hee muſt take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof to bee the more watchfull &amp; warie, leaſt he become one of thoſe that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to carry themſelues diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt men, hee muſt alſo beware leaſt he miniſter occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to another to blame in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that which hee doth blame in his neighbour. A man muſt hold more on <hi>Democritus</hi> then on <hi>Heraclitus</hi> ſide. <hi>Heraclitus</hi> did weepe alwaies at the faults he ſaw men fall into; but <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus</hi> did laugh at them alwaies.</p>
               <p>To the one, all that men doe, did ſeeme to be but miſerie: to the other, fondneſſe and folly.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:20501:74"/>
And it ſeemeth to bee the better of the twaine, when as things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe cannot bee amended, that we ſweeten them a little, if it were but in couering them with the cloake of a faire ſhew, and as it is a thing by all likelihood more conſonant to mans nature, to laugh at the manifold miſeries of our life, then mourningly to bewaile them with teares.</p>
               <p>But yet yee ſhall doe better, if that about the vices of other men, and ſuch as are done in publicke, yee do keepe a medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity and meane, neither alwaies lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, nor yet alwaies laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at them: for it were both a miſerable kinde of diſpoſition, for a man to afflict himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiuely, by reaſon of another mans miſcarriage, and a pitileſſe kinde of paſſe-time alwayes to be laughing thereat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:20501:75"/>But there bee ſome, to whom this aduice will ſeeme to bee of no weight: for not onely they cannot comport with the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of their friends, but alſo thoſe of their enemies doe put them to paine. The honors, the precedencies, the wrongs, the incompetencies vex them: the importunities of their friends, the waywardneſſe, and pieuiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſeruants, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance trouble and torment them daily. But how much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were it to haue patience in ſuch accidents, chiefly ſeeing they winne ſo little by willing and wiſhing the amendment thereof? Yee muſt rather ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine and thinke with your ſelfe, that theſe men, which thus take pleaſure to annoy you, are as dogges which be borne to bark. We muſt impute all this euill to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:20501:75"/>
their peruerſe nature, wherein they are inough puniſhed by the meanes of a perpetuall perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and anguiſh, which pricketh, and pierceth their minde.</p>
               <p>But if your weakeneſſe bee ſuch, as to ſtumble at all that yee ſee ill done, by ſuch as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, yee are then, in that caſe, meerely forlorne. For if the vices of ſtrangers, or of thoſe that be your owne, come once to win ground on you, to cloſe with you, and to ouercome you, yee ſhall be abaſhed, and ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to ſee how that all ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities and troubles, like water, ſhall runne into you, as the raine doth from the gutter into the baſe court, or from a ſteepe hill into a low valley. And out of all queſtion, it is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreetly tender-hearted for a man to be alwaies ſorry and ſad,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:20501:76"/>
if thoſe, with whom we do hant, do not handle, vſe, or entertaine vs ſo carefully, or reſpectiuely as we craue.</p>
               <p>The immoderate affection we beare vnto our ſelues, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, and the delicacy of our condition maketh that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beare with the defects and neglects of our ſeruants, we not conſidering how that very often they know not how to doe any better. Wee require at their hands perfect things, when as yet we our ſelues do fall into ſo many faults, and are ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many imperfections.</p>
               <p>And moſt often wee play the paſſionate and fretting mans part in our ſeruants behalfe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being moued by the diſtaſts that our owne ill conditions doe occaſion vnto vs, or by the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and kinde of the buſineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20501:76"/>
we haue in hand: and thus foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly wee caſt the fault ouer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them which are innocent, and do the beſt they can.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another thing which doth bring vnto vs much diſquiet, and that is to affect too much one and the ſame thing, &amp; thereabout to fall into debate with our friends. For there was neuer yet any perfect friendſhip amongſt them which are led and miſcarried with an obſtinate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and contention who ſhal ouercome. If ye belabor, &amp; accuſtome yourſelfe, through ezerciſe, to frame your ſelfe to times and perſons, ye may eaſily gouerne and rule men at your will, &amp; withall purge them from ſuch euill humours as yee finde them ſubiect vnto. And whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it ſhall fall out, that it ſhall ſeeme vnto you a thing impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb facs="tcp:20501:77"/>
to comport with them; thinke that it is your fault, and that this floweth from your own inability: conſidering how that ſo many others could, and yet can, very well comport with the ſame. For euen as the ſicke are wont to ſay, that they finde all meates bitter, and contrary to their taſte, thinking that the fault is either in the meates, or in the man that prepared them: but as ſoone as they ſee other men eate them, without going anie whit againſt their ſtomacke, they do know that the imperfection lieth in themſelues. In like manner, as often as yee call to minde, how that many others haue ſuffered, and yet doe ſuffer, with a gaye and couragious heart, the moſt troubleſome, and toileſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of the world, yee muſt confeſſe that the fault muſt bee
<pb facs="tcp:20501:77"/>
imputed to your owne feeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to no other thing elſe.</p>
               <p>If the manners and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your wife vexe you, ye muſt bend them, and bow them gently and ſoftly, if it bee poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that by vſing all kinde of milde and amiable meanes. But if your miſ-fortune be ſuch that yee cannot preuaile with her, by way of pleaſing and peaceable perſwaſions, then it behooueth that wiſedome and diſcretion teach you to endure patiently her croſſe-conditions, and to maiſter and diſſemble the euill which yee cannot amend: otherwiſe bee yee ſure yee ſhall turne your houſe into a priſon, your quiet reſt into reſtleſſe coyle, and your good name into an intollerable ſhame.</p>
               <p>In your children require not that ſageneſſe and ſettledneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:20501:78"/>
which ye find in old folkes: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they were not borne old: This age carrieth in it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, the which if ye ſhould endeauour on a ſuddaine to draw to a perfection, ye ſhould vndertake a taske of no ſmall trouble, and if in yong trees ye are conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they beare leaues and buds, why do yee require ripe fruite in your children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time? Who craueth the thing that cannot be had, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for that hee ſhall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine? The meane is to teach, &amp; inſtruct them diligently, to bring them vp vertuouſly, and not to chide them continually, or check them immoderatly: if peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they faile to do a thing as they ought.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="discourse">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:20501:78"/>
               <head>DISC. 16.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Iniuries and Indignities.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere are ſome men, which could patiently comport with all other kind of affliction: onely they cannot away with an indignity and wrong. The which thing, neuertheleſſe, befalleth them more for being perſwaded that the iniurie offered them is vnſupportable, then for that it is ſo of the owne nature. In which caſe, one thing may auaile you much; if yee can reſolue with your ſelfe to keepe you aloofe from the common opinion, and if yee can conſider without paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, each one of the things that are wont thus to toile, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moile mens mindes. For in ſo doing, yee ſhall ſee, if yee haue reaſon to think vpon the wrong
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:20501:79"/>
offered you ſo immoderately as yee do.</p>
               <p>There is one kinde of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which we call an iniurie, or wrong, that is, when any one ouerthwarteth vs in our affaires againſt all equity and right. And there is another kinde, which we call an indignity, or affront, when as in our body, or name, we are vſed by word or deede o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then is fitting.</p>
               <p>For both theſe kindes, yee ought to know, that the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man is not ſubiect to receiue any wrong: not that I do meane that there is none to offer, and inferre wrong, (for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſacred, but there will be found ſacrilegious hands to touch it.) But that though there bee not wanting multitudes of men, whoſe tongues and hands haue no other imployment, but
<pb facs="tcp:20501:79"/>
to defile, and diminiſh, ſo much as in them lyeth, the honour of God, and of men: yet, for all that, the vertuous mans minde is not a whit the leſſe aſſured: and though that ſuch miſchieuous, and malicious men, leuell right at him to hit, and to hurt him with their harmefull ſhaft, yet doe they come ſhort of their aime; for either they hit him not, or if they do, they hurt him not at all for an inuiolable thing is not ſimply that which cannot be hit, but rather that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hit, receiueth thereby no hurt, or at leaſt, careth not at all for it. And thus doth it fare with the vertuous man, who of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe offereth no man any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of offering him any wrong. And if it fall out, than a man, out of a proud &amp; haughty ſtomacke, or rather out of a malitious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:20501:80"/>
ſet vpon him, and aſſaile him; he is then in that caſe like a braſen wall which the dartes of the wicked cannot pierce through.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we know that the vertue and vigour of him, who in fighting hath vanquiſhed his aduerſarie, is alwaies greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mans who neuer did try the combate in his time. And euen the very ſame muſt we think and ſay of the vertuous wight, and wel diſpoſed perſon: who, like to good mettal, the more he is fired the more is hee fined, the more he is oppoſed, the more is he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued. Wrongs may well trie him, touch him, or pricke him, but they cannot imprint in him any falſe ſtampe. And if (perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture) ſome flout, or affront be flung vpon him, as it were, by the way; yet doth he in the mean
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:20501:80"/>
time remaine firme and vnremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, hee maketh no reckoning, nor yet taketh any notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as aſſuring himſelfe that it doth not reach ſo farre as vnto him. Adde alſo hereunto, that there is almoſt no man, but hee will hold the wrong-offerer for wicked, and the wrong-ſufferer for honeſt, as not deſeruing any ſuch outragious vſage. The force and ſtrength of his vertue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo much the more in this kinde of aduerſity, and his mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and meekneſſe of minde, ſhineth ſo much the more clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by how much the more atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and grieuous the wrong offered was. But vnto ſuch as are of a more tender and dainty cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, an indignity is more vnea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be borne withall.</p>
               <p>But would you ſee how men do meaſure wrongs by opinion?
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:20501:81"/>
Such vanity there is in the things of this world, that ſome will make leſſe adoe for a bloudy blow, then for a light box on the eare. Yea ſome will make a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtirre for a vaniſhing harde word, then they would doe for a deadly dint of a ſharpe ſword. Wee are fallen into ſuch blinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and babiſhneſſe, that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion annoyeth vs more then the ſoare it ſelfe, being like vnto little children, which are ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at a mummers maske. If it chance that a man bee hindered, or wronged in his goods, it is a wonder to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what a coyle hee doth keepe about them. But the diſcreet and well-ſtayed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who iudgeth of things ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon, not meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them by opinion, as he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all things, euen as if it were by borrowing ſo he feeleth the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:20501:81"/>
loſſe of them, as if they were things no wiſe his owne. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as he ſhould not ceaſe to be content, though hee had neuer had them at all, ſo he taketh the loſſe of any part of them, as the neceſſary out-caſting or forgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one portion to ſaue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the middeſt of a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous ſtorme. Yea the forgoing of his whole goods will not make him to forget his owne worth, and vigour of minde: he knowing well that not onely his goods, but alſo his life, honour, and whole happineſſe doe hang vpon him who is the giuer of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good thing. Such an one poſſibly hath couzened you of ſo many crownes, hath deceiued you of ſo many Ducates. Well, it is a domage he hath done you, yet is it a loſſe but of a part one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of your goods, and not of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:20501:82"/>
whole. And the man that hath the heart to giue, or forgoe the whole, can he be much ſorry to let go, or looſe a part?</p>
               <p>But if it bee the manner of your loſſe which doth moſt vexe you: then in that caſe yee haue to thinke, that as your vertue would haue you to comport with Fortune and her frownes; ſo ought yee likewiſe to beare with inſolent and audacious men, which are no other thing elſe, but the hookiſh handes of the ſame hard fortune. Truſt me, that our impatiency doth vs much more harme, then thoſe, of whoſe violence, iniuſtice, and wrong wee doe ſo bitterly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine.</p>
               <p>What? (will ſome ſay) ſuch a one did diſdaine to cap to mee; ſuch another in ſpeaking to mee did not vſe that reſpect in my
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:20501:82"/>
behalfe as he ought, &amp; I thought he ſhould haue done: ſuch a one did not giue me place, but ſate him downe before me, and ſuch another would not giue me the wall. What tearms, I pray you, be all theſe, but meere plaints flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the ſoft and feeble cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of an effeminate minde?</p>
               <p>Diuers thinges diſpleaſe vs, which otherwiſe would not do ſo, if we had the skill and will to conſter them aright, and to take them in the better part; whereas through our owne indiſcretion, and diſtruſt of our ſelues, wee make that an indignity which of it owne nature is none, in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wee iudge our ſelues well worthy thereof, and what other thing is it but lacke of courage, though we feele the wrong wee haue receiued neuer ſo ſenſible, not to be able to tread on it, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:20501:83"/>
to trample it vnder feete?</p>
               <p>And if we will but weigh and obſerue how, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the mighty viſions and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of dangers, which do preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in our dreames do ſuddenly euaniſh, ye ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do make vs laugh when as wee remember the ſame, wee ſhould do well to endeauour to do the like in our wrongs, euen to thinke when as any wrong is done vs, that we doe but awake out of a dreaming ſleepe: a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and wel-diſpoſed man (aſſure your ſelfe) will bee loath to wrong you in your body, goods, or good name; and as for any ill-diſpoſed wretch, what ſhall it auaile you to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, ſeeing that he is no more his owne man then if hee were madde? Yee will willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any thing at the hands of a
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:20501:83"/>
man that is out of his wits, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ye make any complaint for ought hee hath ſaid or done to you, but will rather pitty his caſe: in the like manner muſt ye beare with the miſ-behauiour of a fooliſh vndiſcreet perſon, who is no better then a man out of his mind: yee will endure well enough what a Ieſter or ſporter will ſay vnto you, be it neuer ſo vnpleaſant, and would thinke it but a baſe part for you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme againſt, or to complaine vpon ſuch a perſon, and if hee chance to vtter any pleaſing word amidſt his carping diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ye take it and taſt it as a ſauory diſport. Conſider ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how vnfitting and vnſeeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a thing it were that the ſame word vttered by one ſhould make you to laugh, and by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lowre: the caſe ſo ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:20501:84"/>
that the man that is in cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor hath no more iudgement the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſimple Ieſter hath; if hee haue ſo much.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall wee ſay of thoſe that are offended with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle boyes, and ſilly women? perſones that doe offend rather of weakeneſſe then of a wilfull or wicked deſigne? for conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion yee ſhall neuer attaine to tranquility of minde, if yee take in ill part euery croſſe-chance that doth offer it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Some will ſay, this offence may bee well borne with, but that other muſt not bee borne with at all. But theſe men doe ſhut vp vertue into a too ſtraite roome, and confine her abilities within too narrow bounds, as if they ſhould ſay vertue may well vanquiſh this wrong, but not that other, truely if fortune
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:20501:84"/>
be not wholly beaten downe and defeated, ſhe will remaine miſtreſſe. But what if it be ſo, will ye ſay, that I haue giuen ſome occaſion to affront me in this faſhion? how then ſhall I, or can I, beare it patiently and go with an open face? If the iniury hath his birth from your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behauiour, ye muſt thinke then, that it is not ſo much a wrong as a correction: and this yee ought to receiue as a diſcreete man ought to do, and withall make vſe of it as a chaſtiſement of your owne miſcarriage. If it chance that a man floute you for ſome imperfection of your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as for that your noſe, eyes, or legges are not to their mind, take not this to heart as a reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable wrong: for it is but a meere folly, for a man to care much for that which falleth not
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:20501:85"/>
out through his owne faults. <hi>Fidus Cornelius</hi> did weepe for very anger in the Senate, becauſe <hi>Corduba Struthio</hi> ſaid to him ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly that he did reſemble much a pilde Camell: ſee what ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if one counterfeit our geſture, loe wee are by and by offended. But what miſerable blindneſſe is it for a man to vex himſelfe becauſe another doth imitate his mode or manner of going. The meane were rather to do thus, if nature hath laid vpon you any defect or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh which doth deforme your body, which yee cannot couer, that your ſelfe were the firſt man ſhould ſpeake of it, as knowing it better then any other: for by this meanes ye ſhall take away from others all occaſion of ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or flouting you for the ſame: Thus <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atinius</hi> was wont
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:20501:85"/>
to mocke himſelfe, in regard of his necke, and feete which were ſomewhat deformed: ſo that his enemies and ilwillers could not take any aduantage thereof to breake vpon him any bitter ieſt. Moreouer it is not a ſmall policy to depriue the party that doth you wrong of all the pleaſure hee entendeth to reape, by hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your peace, as not thinking him worthy of ſo much as one word of your mouth, or by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him there where ye found him, as diſdaining to brable or quarell with him, or yet to take any notice of the man, or of his manners: if ye will be aduiſed by me, make neuer anſwere to an inſolent malapert perſon, for in holding your tongue ye leaue with him lying in his mouth, yea in his minde, his vice, folly, and raſhneſſe, whereas in anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:20501:86"/>
him, ye ſhal conforme your ſelfe to his naughty nature. There is nothing that equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth ſo much men among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as the participation of one and the ſame vice: neither can there any ſuch chaſtiſement befall vnto an ill-humored man as to make no reckoning, but to let vaniſh with the winde his vaine and vnſauory words, for both by your ſilence are his ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned of impertinency, &amp; he depriued of the pleaſure he promiſed to himſelfe by prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you to anger.</p>
               <p>It behoueth likewiſe a man to be very circumſpect and warie in his ieſting at others. For we find by experience that men do commonly flie the company of ſuch as make profeſſion of ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing and mocking others. We find likewiſe that no man can
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:20501:86"/>
entertaine certaine amitie and vnfaileable friendſhip with ſuch an one as is auerſe from pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch as haue offended him. The Emperour <hi>Caius Caeſar,</hi> a man of an iniurious inclination, had in his armie a certaine Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bune, <hi>Cherea</hi> by name; a man of a ſhrill, ſmall and womaniſh voyce in ſpeaking, and therefore one of whom they had no great opinion. This womaniſh-voiced man hauing on a time asked the Emperour what ſhould bee the watch-word: he of purpoſe to ſcorn him gaue him ſuch a word as was diſhoneſt. By reaſon of which indignity the Tribune was ſo deeply offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that therafter aſſociating himſelfe among the murtherers which did wickedly ſeaſe vpon the Emperour, he was the man who with one blow did beate downe the one halfe of his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:20501:87"/>
braines. So that he who ſeemed vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> to come ſomewhat ſhort of a man, proued moſt the man (though indeede he had more malice then man-hood in his heart) in cutting off impiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Caeſar</hi> from being any more a man &amp; a Monarch among men. To vſe ſuch bitter taunts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth want of diſcretion, and not to be able to digeſt them, doth argue lacke of courage. <hi>Socrates</hi> hearing himſelfe flouted to his face, did no other thing but laugh thereat, without making any ſhew of a diſpleaſed mind. It is reported of him and of <hi>Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the Romane, that they two did ſo happily entertaine this <hi>Tranquility of mind,</hi> that they were neuer ſeene to change their countenance.</p>
               <p>Moreouer ye ought diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to auoide all noyſe, brables
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:20501:87"/>
and ſtrife: for this brawling and quarrelling humour altereth not a little the whole man, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ill-conditioned. Be not lauiſh of your language, but rather ſparing of ſpeech. Let your words bee ſuch as carry with them their due authority and weight. And withall accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome your ſelfe to paſſe diuerſe things vnder the great ſeale of ſure ſilence.</p>
               <p>Suffer not your ſelfe to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled by the vnreaſonable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the miſordered mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, which doe hold ſuch folkes onely to bee free as may do what ere they liſt, be it neuer ſo euill, and ſuch onely to bee couragious and generous ſpirits as can put vp no wrong.</p>
               <p>It is true liberty for a man to liue not according as his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe luſt doth lead him, but as
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:20501:88"/>
reaſon doth rule him: and to do not what euer ſenſually hee would, but what reaſonable he ſhould, And it is true courage and magnanimity for a man to put vp wrongs, to miſteeme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to bee moued by them, but to command his affections, and to ouercome his paſſions. That which the man ſhall neuer be able to do, who hath not his ſpirit compoſed, and his minde ordered to deſpiſe theſe vanities and delicacies, which doe ſhake the feebler ſort: finally endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to haue the vpper hand in ſetting light by all humane croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and popular conceits: for it is no ſigne of good health when a man is alwaies crying &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining that they touch him, &amp; in the ſame manner it fareth with the minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="discourse">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:20501:88"/>
               <head>DISC. 17.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Pouerty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE man that can make but that reckoning of life and death that he ought, I feare not that pouerty can afflict him, or yet bereaue him of his reſt, For it were a thing very vnfitting that hee who can deſpiſe death, ſhould ſuffer his courage to bee caſt downe, let alone, to bee quite quelled by pouerty and neede, which neuertheleſſe is the thing the common people doth moſt apprehend, and moſt plaine vpon, when as they cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain vnto a ſufficiencie of goods whereupon to maintaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a gay and gallant man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. They not being able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues with ſuch things as may ſerue for their neceſſity;
<pb facs="tcp:20501:89"/>
but eſteeming aboundance and wealth mans ſoueraigne good; and pouerty, and want his ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine euill. And yet were it not better for a man not to haue a thing, then to looſe it when he hath it? And how is it poſſible in this life that ſome ſhould not looſe, ſeeing that one cannot be rich, except many other bee poore, and many cannot inherit, except others do dye? And yet there is in pouerty this conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that as it is not ſubiect to the receiuing, and incurring of great damages, ſo is it not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſo many mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous turmoiles as plenty and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance is.</p>
               <p>And to thinke that rich men haue more courage to comport with loſſes then other men haue, it is an errour. For the paine of a ſoare is as ſenſible and dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:20501:89"/>
in a bigge body, as in a ſmall; yea we fee ordinarily, that the greateſt men are the moſt tender and delicate.</p>
               <p>The Philoſopher <hi>Bion</hi> was wont to ſay, that the paine is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like which is felt by plucking, or pulling the haires from an head that hath many, and from that which hath few.</p>
               <p>All the difference that can be, is this; that the balde head hath leſſe haire to looſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot feele ſo much ſmart as the other doth that is ful of haires.</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that we ſee, for the moſt part, the poorer ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be more iocund and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then commonly the richer ſort are, becauſe they haue not ſo great care as they haue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they feare ſo deeply the ſtorme of aduerſity, as the richer
<pb facs="tcp:20501:90"/>
ſort doe. For they are eaten vp with this double worm, the care of conſeruing and increaſing the goods they haue got, and the feare of looſing that which they enioy. But pouerty is a Caſtle and fort, aſſured and fenced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fortune, yea the whole world. She feareth nothing and is able with all to defend herſelfe againſt all her enemies.</p>
               <p>Thou man whoſoeuer thou art that goeſt drooping &amp; dying for riches, for worldly pelfe, and wealth, tell mee I pray thee, if ſince thou haſt got them, they haue brought vnto thee any more knowledge vnto thy minde, or more tranquility and peace vnto thy ſpirit, or more reſt and happineſſe vnto thine heart, then thou hadſt before, they came into thine hands? The wiſe men among the heathen
<pb facs="tcp:20501:90"/>
haue taught vs, how much po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty is to be priſed and praiſed, when as they did portrait and paint their Gods naked, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto them all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they conceited to bee moſt befitting their natures: and as for my ſelfe, I ſhall neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that man poore who is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced without the reach &amp; power of fortune. There is one thing ſufficient to expreſſe vnto vs the nature of pouerty, to wit, that no vertuous man ſpeaketh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but he praiſeth it, and auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that the wiſeſt haue beene thoſe who haue ſuffered the ſame with moſt contentment, and truly it is a great weakneſſe and tenderneſſe in vs not to bee able to endure that which ſo many others haue well endured, and it can be no other thing but a vaine apprehenſion and a friuoulous
<pb facs="tcp:20501:91"/>
feare of enduring and ſuffering which maketh vs ſo feeble hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for if we were indeed of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous &amp; magnanimous diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we would loue and like that for our ſelues which we approue in others, and therefore howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer that this peeuiſhneſſe and ſoftneſſe of ours is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be comported with; wee ought at leaſt to limite our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and dreſſe our ſelues in ſuch ſort that fortune may finde the leſſe aduantage to offend vs, for a little body that can couer, &amp; gather it ſelfe together vnder a buckler marcheth on towards the enemy, much more ſurely then a bigger body doth, that lyeth at large and open vnto blowes, If it were not mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to husband the time, &amp; to ſpare paper, I could enlarge my diſcourſe by reciting of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:20501:91"/>
innumerable examples aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of heathens as of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which haue placed a great part of their perfection in pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But yee ought to conſider one thing for all, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> was poore, who was Lord of the whole world: his Diſciples were poore, which did poſſeſſe all things, and the Saints were poore which might haue beene rich. If yee ſhould neuer dye, I would aduiſe you to ſet your affection vpon riches, but I ſee that thoſe to whom they moſt befall, doe finde ſooner the end of their liuing then of their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. But why ſhould a man torment himſelfe for a thing that hee muſt neceſſarily leaue? and why is he not rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent quietly with that which is needfull, chiefly conſidering that the faireſt kinde of wealth
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:20501:92"/>
is for a man to bee neither too poore, nor yet too farre off from pouerty?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="discourse">
               <head>DISC. 18.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Death.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT ſeemeth that all incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and miſ-fortunes may bee borne with, either by the meanes of a long cuſtome, or by the helpe of a ſtrong diſcourſe, onely death and the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, is the thing that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs in greateſt feare.</p>
               <p>Now the onely remedy and true eaſing of this euill, is that ye make this reckoning of the world, and all that is therein, that yee haue nothing which is your owne, neither life, nor li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, no not ſo much as your owne ſelfe: but that yee liue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies at borrowing, as holding
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:20501:92"/>
your very life, not in property but on condition to reſtore it vnto him againe, who hath lent it you, whenſoeuer hee ſhall require it at your hands: yet for all this yee muſt not not neglect it as thing not yours, but muſt keepe it faithfully, and carefully in regard that God hath truſted you with the cuſtody thereof, and when it is time, to render it to him that gaue it, not grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gingly, but gladly, and with a cheerefull countenance, in the meane time thanking God, the giuer of all good things, for the time ye haue had the vſe and aid thereof, and ſaying vnto him in this or the like manner; Lord, I render vnto thee againe this ſoule, and life, with as good an hart as it pleaſed thee to giue me the ſame, yea euen euen with a better and readier will then I did
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:20501:93"/>
receiue it, for when thou gaueſt me this ſoule, thou gaueſt it to a little weake creature, which knew not the good thou then didſt beſtow, but now thou doſt receiue it againe at the hands of a creature, more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, who knoweth what it is hee commendeth into thine hands, and therefore rendereth it vnto thee, withall frankneſſe and readineſſe of will: and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may eaſily imagine that it is not a thing otherwiſe difficult for a ſubſtance to returne to the the p ace whence it firſt came, the body therefore muſt returne to the earth, and the ſoule (if it go the right way) muſt goe to him that gaue it. To bee ſhort, that man doubtleſly neuer lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned well to iue, who knoweth not how to die: we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this caſe bee ſo affected
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:20501:93"/>
towards our ſelues, as wee are wont to be in the behalfe of fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers which muſt fight in a barred field, for wee commonly hate him that beareth himſelfe faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedly, and fauour the other who out of a braue courage had rather chooſe to dye then to bee ouercome. Beſides that the feare of death is ſometimes the cauſe, or occaſion of death, to him that flyeth faſteſt from it.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing yee know well, that life was giuen you vpon condition to render it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ought not to be ſo vniuſt, as to deſire to enioy that thing for aye, which was giuen vnto you to a day, by making your ſelfe Lord, and owner of the thing whereof yee are onely a depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie or keeper.</p>
               <p>Moreouer men will ſay, that it is a matter much importing,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:20501:94"/>
to wit, the feare, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of death, and that it is the extreame of all terrible things. But ye ought to vnderſtand that Death is not to bee found fault with for this, ſeeing that it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from the nature of death, but from our owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becility: who are commonly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken and intangled with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, with a deſire of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory life, and with an immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate loue of this miſerable fleſh? And if yee take good heede, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe that is dreadfull, as the opinion which wee hold concerning the ſame. For euery man feareth it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his iudgment, apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and conſcience.</p>
               <p>And if it be ſo, that yee haue no feare thereof, but onely for this occaſion, then lay the blame vpon your ſelfe, and not vpon
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:20501:94"/>
it. For in this caſe it fareth with men of euill conſcience, when they muſt dye, as it doth riotous ſpend-thrifts when they muſt pay their debts. They will not come to an account for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt which they haue of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to ſatisfie for what they haue done.</p>
               <p>And to ſay that ye feare death, by reaſon that it is the laſt point and periode of man, hath but little reaſon in it. For the ſoule is alwaies the fore, it liueth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, and cannot dye.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Greekes</hi> call mans deceaſe, the end, giuing vs thereby to vnderſtand, that it is the period and end of weariſome life.</p>
               <p>The holy Scripture calleth it a ſleep, to aſſure vs of an aſſured reſurrection, and to the end wee weepe not, as the Infidels doe, which are without hope, Let vs
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:20501:95"/>
conſider with our ſelues how many holy men and women haue priſed it, and deſired it as the onely eaſement of all their anguiſh.</p>
               <p>The writes of <hi>Salomon, Iob,</hi> and the Hiſtories of Gods Saints are ful of the praiſes of this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian deſire of death. What a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is it to loue ſo much this miſerable life, this Iaile, this priſon, this vale of teares, ſeeing that the longer we liue, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wee liue in ſinne, the more daies we ſpend, the more waies wee offend, and ſo goe on each houre purchaſing vnto our ſelues a new paine and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>Finally, to ſhut the doore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all fearefull apprehenſions of death, we muſt learne to do two things which the world can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer teach vs; the one is to liue
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:20501:95"/>
well, for a vertuous and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an life maketh euen agreeabe the very memory of death: the other is that we beleeue that the thing which it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to affoord vs for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and eaſement of our manifold labours, and toyles is not ſo harſh, nor ſo horrible, as we do imagine it is.</p>
               <p>And for a finall concluſion, let vs remember, how that the Saints haue had life in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and death in affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:96"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:20501:96"/>
               <head>The Authors Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EHOLD here the floures that I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered here &amp; there out of the garden of the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing wits and writs of the wiſe, which I haue paſſed mine eies ouer. Them I lay out in common betweene you and me, euen as the buſie bees do in their hiues with all they haue reaped in the faire and well furniſhed gardens, or flourie fields, to the end we together may draw out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:20501:97"/>
the ſugred hony of this ſweet and pleaſant <hi>Tranquility of mind.</hi> I am of the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for my part, that if the ancient po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets had throughly knowne thereof, they would not haue put themſelues in paine to compoſe any other <hi>Nectar</hi> or brue any other <hi>Ambroſia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, for the diet of their gods: but ſhould haue thoght them well feaſted in ſeruing them with this diſh alone, for all meſſes and at meales. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore we haue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity offered vs of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and vſing ſo diuine a thing, let vs make vſe of it in the moſt thrifty manner wee poſſible may: acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the meane time that
<pb facs="tcp:20501:97"/>
this <hi>Tranquility</hi> we talke of, is a gift from heauen, which the bountifull influence of the worlds-maker muſt diſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our minds; hee being the true and liuing well-ſpring whence floweth all our felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and bliſſe. Whoſe name therefore (according as wee are bound) wee bleſſe and magnifie for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
